<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The young man's duty A discourse shewing the necessity of seeking the Lord betimes; as also the danger and unreasonableness in trusting to a late, or death-bed repentance. Designed especially for young persons, before they are debauched by evil company, and evil habits. By Rich. Kidder M.A.</title>
            <author>Kidder, Richard, 1633-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47345</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828881</idno>
  <idno type="VID">33314</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240869803</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing K420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217183</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828881</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828881e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47345)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33314)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1970:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The young man's duty A discourse shewing the necessity of seeking the Lord betimes; as also the danger and unreasonableness in trusting to a late, or death-bed repentance. Designed especially for young persons, before they are debauched by evil company, and evil habits. By Rich. Kidder M.A.</title>
                  <author>Kidder, Richard, 1633-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 188, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by H.L. for George Calvert and Samuel Sprint at the Golden Ball in Duck-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a vertical half-title on verso of p.[20]: The young man's duty.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Youth --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Young Man's Duty.</hi> A Discourse Shewing The Necessity of seeking the Lord betimes, as also the Danger and Unreasonableness in trusting to a late OR, <hi>Death-bed-repentance.</hi> Designed especially for <hi>Young Persons,</hi> before they are debauched by evil Company, and evil Habits.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICH. KIDDER</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Marc. Antonin lib. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>George Calvert</hi> and <hi>Samuel Sprint</hi> at the Golden Ball in <hi>Duck-lane.</hi> 1671.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:3"/>
            <head>THE Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Author of these Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers do easily foresee, that this following Discourse will not be welcom to sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry sorts of Readers: As for those that are curious, and that are pleased only with <hi>Novelties,</hi> he expects to be despised by such. For he knows, that these <hi>Athenians</hi> spend their time in hearing or telling some new thing, and he will not wonder that these men should call him <hi>Babler.</hi> Nor does he much value the Censures of those men that had rather be <hi>learned</hi> then <hi>holy.</hi> But yet he hopes, if the following Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course carry with it <hi>truth,</hi> that he shall not deserve a Censure, because it is not <hi>trim</hi> as well as <hi>true:</hi> For as he was
<pb facs="tcp:33314:4"/>at first cast upon these Meditations, to supply the necessities of such as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired all plainness of speech, so it is now made publick for the benefit of such; And if to any such, whose hearts are better then their heads, this Treatise shall afford any spiritual ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, the Author will most cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully undergo the scorn of the more curious Reader: since his design in publishing these things was, not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the Reader with quaint and aiery forms of speech, but, faithfully to represent to him the great necessity of reformation in heart and life. And certainly, it would be a great Piece of vanity in so weighty a matter as this is, to flourish with affected and osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatious forme of speech; And some men would question the truth of what we say; if we should dress our Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses in such a Pedantry as Boyes do their Declamations. That man would be very cruel, that should see his Neighbours house on fire, but yet
<pb facs="tcp:33314:4"/>would not give his Neighbour notice of his danger, till he had studied a quaint speech to deliver the sad tidings with. When the flames of Hell are approaching apace to the men we preach to, the danger will command us to be <hi>earnest,</hi> but not oblige us to be <hi>eloquent.</hi> We must rather do as the Angels did by <hi>Lot,</hi> who instead of holding him with an eloquent Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue, told him plainly of the danger that did approach, and while he lingred, laid their hands on him, and brought him out of the City.</p>
            <p>To others this following Discourse will be unwelcom, not onely because it hath been so hardy to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in publick, when there are so many Books already that can finde no Entertainment; But also because this Argument hath already been handled by men of great worth and name. And indeed it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied that the world is too full
<pb facs="tcp:33314:5"/>of Books, and that this Subject hath bin insisted on by men of great abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But then every one does not meet with what hath been said, nor can eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one understand them, and there are very few that heed them, and yet is the thing it self of very great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the souls of men. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, considering how frequently men delude themselves with a promise of death-bed Repentance, and how they transgress in the mean time, and make their Accounts swell, and the Author having had too much sad experience of the prevailing of this conceit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong those that have bin committed to his care, thought himself obliged to bear witness against such a mistake as is at once both very <hi>common</hi> and very <hi>pernicious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there is another sort of Readers, who though they may peruse the things that are here offered, and let them pass without a censure, will not be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to an effectual and speedy Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.
<pb facs="tcp:33314:5"/>The most undeniable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, the most passionate Exhortations, the most earnest Intreaties will not prevail with them presently to forsake all their sins, and to love and serve God. They will still put the evil day far from them, and promise themselves <hi>time</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> enough to repent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; and if one should arise from the <hi>dead,</hi> and from the <hi>damned,</hi> yet would they not be perswaded to make haste. These men are buried in sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sual delights and pleasures, and have acquainted themselves with those things only that gratifie and please the animal life, they have bin brought up in sin and foolish pleasures, and taught to admire the pomp and gaiety of this present world, and to pursue earnestly the designs of their pride, and lust, and covetousness, and think that a little after-care about their souls, a few hopeful words at last will satisfie Almighty God for all. They know some care must be taken about their
<pb facs="tcp:33314:6"/>souls before they die, that they must repent and amend, and this they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve to do some time before their death.</p>
            <p>I shall not forbear to say some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to such a man that thus delays his repentance, over and above what he may find in the ensuing Discourse, by which it will appear, however he may deceive his own soul, that when he puts off his repentance to hereafter, in all probability he will never repent at all, but die in his sins, and be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable to all eternity. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince such a man, that this may very justly be presumed and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ared, I shall desire him to consider with me the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Severals, which will make it very probable, that whereas he sayes he will repent hereafter, that yet be will never repent at all.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Consider, thou that sayest thou wilt repent <hi>hereafter,</hi> what should be the reason why thou canst not do it <hi>now;</hi> and whether the very same
<pb facs="tcp:33314:6"/>reason that hinders thee from reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>now,</hi> will not <hi>always</hi> hinder thee: Say what it is, thou that makest these delays, that keeps thee from reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing presently; it is the want of power to do it; and how dost thou know thy ability will be greater hereafter then now? Is it because the Rules of the Gospel are severe and strict, and will they not be as severe hereafter as now they are? Or doest thou hope, that God will unbend his Laws, which are unalterable, and stoop to thy prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness? Or doest thou delay thy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, because thy sins are many and great, and thou despairest of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? And will not the heap be as great hereafter as now? Is it thy worldly business, and will it not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be so? That which now hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thee, will always do so, till it is taken out of the way: things standing as they are, the issue and event must needs be the same.
<pb facs="tcp:33314:7"/>That which makes thee unfit <hi>to day,</hi> wil make thee as unfit <hi>to morrow;</hi> Nay <hi>2.</hi> More unfit.<note place="margin">Citius sibi plagarum caro sociat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r quod non diu hiaro per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur. <hi>Salv. ad Eccl. Cath l.</hi> 1.</note> Thou art like to be more unfit every day then other. It is here as in a wound or sore, the longer it continues, the more hard it is to cure it, whereas a timely dressing may cure it quickly: A dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease that is timely taken is easily cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but if it stay till it have altered the blood, and have amassed together a load of filth, and destroyed the tone and strength of the Principal Parts, and brought in a general ill habit of body; it maey then be past all remedy. Whatever unfits thee now, will make thee much more unfit hereafter. For as the work will then be more hard, so will thy strength be weaker, thy time shorter, thy discouragements greater, and thy temptations and objections more and more strong then they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore. He that thinks of repenting on
<pb facs="tcp:33314:7"/>his death-bed, should remember that he will have a greater task to do, and less time and strength to do it in then now he hath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If thy sins are so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many and so great now, that thou dost almost despair of mercy, certainly they will be more and greater then: if it be troublesom to thee now to look back upon thy old scores, sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there will be more of labour and discouragement in it, to undo and unravel the many sins of a long life: if now thou thinkest the Commands of Christ severe and strict, certainly hereafter, when thou hast been more engaged in sin, and longer wedded to the world, and thy lusts are faster riveted to thy soul, thou wilt think more hardly of a holy life, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Christ will be more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to thee. If now it be so hard a task, what wilt thou think it when thy day is almost spent, and
<pb facs="tcp:33314:8"/>thy Sun a setting! if it be hard now to cast out the unclean spirit, and bind the strong man; What a task will it be when there are more evil spirits to cast out.</hi> If the Ethiopian can change his skin, or the Leopard his spots, then may ye also do good, that are accustomed to do evil.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. Consider, thou that sayest thou wilt repent hereafter, whether thou hast not formerly promised to repent, and yet broken thy word, and if thou hast, why shouldest thou believe thy self again. Didst thou never upon some sick bed, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der some great danger, make a Vow, that if God would deliver thee, he should be thy God; and yet for all that, when the danger hath been over, thou haft returned to thy sins and evil ways again. And hast thou not as much reason as ever to think, that as thou didst then but dissemble with God, so
<pb facs="tcp:33314:8"/>now thou didst but mock him. Thy deceitful heart is still in thy breast, and as ready to impose upon thee as ever it was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4. Consider, thou that sayst thou wilt repent</hi> tomorrow, <hi>when this</hi> morrow <hi>will come; Thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> hereafter <hi>thou sayest, but that is an uncertain and</hi> unlimited word, <hi>whereas God</hi> limiteth a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain day, <hi>saying,</hi> To day if ye will hear his voice, <hi>Heb. 4.7. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</hi> Behold, now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>2 Cor. 6.2. God says</hi> Now, <hi>we say</hi> Hereafter: <hi>God says</hi> to day; <hi>we say,</hi> tomorrow: <hi>Gods time is come, but when will our time come? It is a worthy saying of one of the Ancients,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That,</hi> tomorrow hath no end. And it were well if it were not too often verified in the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous delay of sinners,<note place="margin">Modo &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:33314:9"/>
               <hi>whose</hi> tomorrow <hi>and</hi> hereafter <hi>hath many times no bounds or stops, and is as far from coming to an end, as an Eternity it self. For he that makes delays makes no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress at all, and is therefore very elegantly compared by</hi> Solomon, <hi>to</hi> a door that is turned upon its hinges, <hi>Prov. 26: 14. For as such a door, though it may be opened and clap'd too, yet makes no progress at all, being held by the hinges to which it is fastened: so the slothful sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is held fast by his delays till he be unhinged by a very effectual change. He that uses delays, how fair soever he speak, yet does not advance at all: He is like the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermost wheels of a Chariot or Coach, which are indeed near the foremost wheels, and seem to run with a design to overtake them, but yet being fastned to a lower Axel-tree, they never make any nearer approaches to them,</hi>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33314:9"/>
                  <l>Nam quamvis prope te, quamvis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone sub uno,</l>
                  <l>Vertentem sese, frustra sectabere Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thum,</l>
                  <l>Cum rota posterior curras &amp; in axe se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. There is no end of these de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays; They are the devils device to draw thee into an inevitable destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; 'tis the Sluggard that says,</hi> Yet a little sleep, a littbe slumber, a little folding of the hands to sleep, so shall his Poverty come as one that travelleth, and his want as an Armed man. <hi>The Devil can well endure thou shouldest promise to reform hereafter, as long as in the mean time thou livest in thy sins. But it is a great peradventure whether e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we shall repent or not, if we do not do it presently. For 'tis likely that he that promises</hi> tomorrow <hi>to
<pb facs="tcp:33314:10"/>begin his repentance (and perhaps hath done for some years past,) should, when</hi> tomorrow <hi>comes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise the next day, and so onwards till there be no time left to run out. This is well exprest by the Satyrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Cras hoc fiet; idem cras fiet; quid. quasi magnum</l>
               <l>Nempe diem donas. Sed cum lux al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera venit.</l>
               <l>Jam cras besternum consumsimus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud cras.</l>
               <l>Egerit hos annos, &amp; semper panlum erit ultra.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tomorrow</hi> shall my work be done,</l>
               <l>Or, when <hi>tomorrow</hi>'s past and gone.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:33314:10"/>
               <l> The next day shall <hi>my morrow</hi> be,</l>
               <l>A day shall break no squares with me.</l>
               <l>He grants too little that doth give</l>
               <l>But one day both to turn and live.</l>
               <l>But when another day's come on,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>first tomorrow</hi>'s fled and gone,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Another morrow</hi> then makes haste,</l>
               <l>And our remaining time doth waste,</l>
               <l>And thus we make no stops, but say</l>
               <l>We still expect another day.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore I shall earnestly beseech the Reader to use no more vain delays, but to hasten out of his sins, and immediately to turn unto the Lord his God, who will
<pb facs="tcp:33314:11"/>be better to him then all his world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profits and pleasures can. This if he do at all, he must do quickly:</hi> We must tread upon thorns while our shoes are upon our feet: <hi>There can be no fitter opportunity then the present to set upon this work. He that depends upon his last houre is like to be deceived: The Jews have a saying to this purpose worth our heeding</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> i. e. He that puts off the houre, the hours shall put him off. <hi>He that neglects the present season out of hopes of one to come, is likely to he deceived at last.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the Lord grant, that what is here offered may do good to the souls of men. That we may so effectually lay these things to heart, that they may not make for our condemnation at that great day. If the Reader receive any advantage by what is here offered, the Author desires him
<pb facs="tcp:33314:11"/>first to give God the praise, and then to pray for him that hath made these things publike, that when he preaches to others, he himself may not be a cast-away.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:12"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:13"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33314:13"/>
            <head>The Young Man's DƲTY &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here cannot be a more dangerous, nor is there a more prevailing error among those that call themselvs Christians then this, that though we lead our lives as we list, yet we shall be undoubtedly happy here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, if upon our Death-beds it repent us of our sins; when yet by repenting we mean no more, but a crying unto God for mercy, and a crying out upon our selves as great sinners: If we can, like the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, become streight before we die, though our whole life were crooked and perverse, we shall think well of our selves, and shall be thought to have made a godly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33314:14"/>and comfortable end, and to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questionably gone to a better place. Thus will a charitable Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borhood judge, and perhaps the Preacher too at the Funerals will considently pronounce it, and then 'tis easily believed; and every sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner comforts up himself in his evil ways, and thinks to get to Heaven at last at as cheap a rate. By this means the great purposes of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel are made void, and the design of our Saviours appearing defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Men think a good life is not of absolute necessity in order to their future happiness, and they take no longer care how they live, the most they aim at is, that they may die with a parcel of good words in their mouths. They run on in their sins in the mean-while, and think it will be soon enough to repent when they make their Wills, or when they lie a dying: Thus the poor sinner is blinded, and makes haste
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33314:14"/>to fill up the measure of his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and repents not till he do it with the flames of Hell about him, till it be too late, and to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. Many that are now in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal torments, made haste to them with these foolish hopes about them: And we that remain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them are posting on apace to the same lamentable destruction; I shall endeavour, with Gods assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to disabuse such men as these, and to shew them their great mistake, before they feel the sad effects of it in sorrows that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable. I shall shew the very great untruth, as well as the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness, and infinite danger of this conceit, and take off all those popular pretences and exceptions which the sinner can bring to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm himself in his misbelief. God Almighty grant, that what is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered may be a means to stop the sinner in his career, and send him
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33314:15"/>home to himself, and to his God. I do conjure the Reader, as he loves his own soul, and as he would not be eternally miserable, that he would consider seriously what is here offered, that he would do it in his retirement and calmest thoughts, reflecting how far he is concerned in these things: I shall proceed and shew the great vanity of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit by sundry Arguments.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>And first of all, this will appear to be a great mistake, if we do but consider duly the nature of true repentance; which (however we thrust it into a narrow room) we shall find to be a duty more difficult and comprehensive, and which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires more time and pains then men are generally apt to believe it does. For though we frequently
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33314:15"/>of Repentance, and pretend to it, and hear it preached of, yet, I feare, it is but little understood and less practised; and when men so little understand what Repentance is, it is no wonder that they mistake so widely in this whole Affair. The doctrine of Repentance is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the spiritual building, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. which if it be not well laid, we build our house upon the Sands, and such an house must needs fall, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.27. Before I come to shew what Repentance is, I shall vindicate it from those mistakes that men are in about it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are much mistaken that think Repentance no more but a parcel of good words, a loud cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God for mercy, and exclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against our selves as great sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; This we can easily do, and love our sins nevertheless when we have done; It breaks none of our bones to do this, it puts us to no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33314:16"/>pain at all, nay, we can do it, and yet be inwardly pleased with our sin in the mean-while; This is all the Repentance that many men have or aim at; They sin, and they confess; but then they sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and confess again, and keep this round while they live. Many men do that which a little before they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest was their sin,<note place="margin">Eadem pené om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes jugiter faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, quae fecisse se plangunt. <hi>Salv. de Gub. Dei lib. 3.</hi>
                  </note> and they will confess it again presently, and yet go on to commit again the same things. <hi>This black Circle</hi> (as one well said) <hi>of Sin, and confess, Confess and sin, encompasses as well Protestants as Papists.</hi> We think ourselves very safe in this Circle, and that our sins cannot do us more hurt then our confession does us good; But certainly, we have very base and low thoughts of God, if we think to charm and cheat him thus easily, if we think
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33314:16"/>he will be mocked with such inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual confessions as these are; What man would endure such usage as this! Will our Neighbour be pleased with us, because we confess we have done him wrong, when he sees we continue to do so still. This were indeed an easie way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a very sick man, and the most guilty might soon do this; I shall transcribe the words of a grave Author upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion; <hi>If,</hi> says he,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>W. Rawleigh</hi> his Preface to the History of the World.</note>
                  <hi>according to St.</hi> Peter, <hi>the righteous shall scarcely be saved, and that God spared not his Angels, where shall those ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, who having served their appetites all their lives, presume to think that the severe Commandments of the All-Powerful God were given but in sport, and that the short breath we draw when death presseth us, if we can but fashion it to the sound of mercy, is sufficient?— But what shall we call a disesteeming,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33314:17"/>an opposing, or (indeed) a mocking of God; if those men do not oppose him, disesteem him and make him, that think it enough for God, to ask him forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness at leisure, with the remainder and last drawing of a malicious breath? For what do they otherwise that die this kind of well-dying, but say unto God as followeth? We beseech thee, O God, that all the falshoods, for swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and treacheries of our lives past, may be pleasing unto thee; that thou wilt for our sakes, (that have had no leisure to do any thing for thine) change thy nature (though impossible) and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to be a just God; that thou wilt love injuries and oppressions; call Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Wisdom; and Charity, foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. — Certainly these wise World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings have either found out a new God, or made one; and in all likelihood, such a leaden one as</hi> Lewis <hi>the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth wore in his Cap; which when he caused any that he feared or hated, to be killed, he would take it from his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33314:17"/>head and kiss it, beseeching it to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him this one evil Act more, and it should be the last; Mockeries indeed fit to be used towards a leaden, but not towards the everliving God:</hi> Thus he. Certainly, the Devil can well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure we should confess our sins, if we forsake them not; we shall not much disturb him by speaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his works, if we destroy them not. These are words of course, that neither trouble the devil, nor yet please God. The Souldiers of Christ must fight, as well as thus bid defiance against his sins. <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> tells us, that when <hi>Memnon</hi> heard one of his Souldiers to ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l against the <hi>Grecian</hi> King, against whom he was entertained to fight, that he stroke him with his Lance, and told him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Plut. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pophegm.</note>
                  <hi>He did not maintain him to rail, but to fight against</hi> Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander. Certainly we shall shew at once more courage, as well as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33314:18"/>more sincerity, by forsaking our sins then by speaking evil of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are much mistaken that think all sorrow that arises in their minds, upon occasion of their sins, is true Repentance. As if any sorrow, occasioned by reason of our sins, were that sorrow which is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a godly sort. Such men are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to think, that a melancholick fit, a few sighs and groans, an hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down the head like a bulrush, and a retiring a while from our mirth and company, a soure face, and moist eyes make up the whole and summe of Repentance. This certainly is a very wide mistake, for though this sorrow may be a step to, or a companion of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, yet alone it comes much short of the main work. For such men as these many times dislike the punishment, not the fault, and grieve not so much because them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves are wicked, as because God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33314:18"/>is just. Their sin brings a trouble upon them, it is the <hi>trouble,</hi> not the <hi>sin</hi> that makes them sorrowful. They have a certain Presage of the uneasiness of the flames of hell, their galled and a king conscience flies in their faces, they feel heavy strokes upon their hearts, for those sins which the World does not see; This makes them pale, and dumpish, when they receive upon their souls the lesser strokes of Hell, and when they see the hand-writing point at them.— <hi>Tacita sudant praecordia cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa.</hi> This will make the stoutest son of <hi>Anak</hi> bend, and yet does it not make him a true Penitent. For the most wicked men may repent at this rate, and many times does it: Thus <hi>Judas,</hi> when he had betrayed our Saviour, when he saw he was condemned, <hi>repented himself,</hi> Mat. 27.3. That is, his Conscience had told him he had done greatly amiss in that <hi>he had betrayed innocent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33314:19"/>blood,</hi> v. 4. He had a great sorrow upon him, a most excessive grief upon his minde, so great and so pressing, that there are that are ready to think, that (however our Translation tell us, that he went and <hi>hanged himself</hi>) he died of grief and sorrow,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that there was no other thing that strangled and choaked him but that; For it is thought, the word which we translate <hi>hang'd himself,</hi> signifies being oppress'd with grief and melancholy, with a sorrow so far from a godly sorrow, that it worketh death; <hi>Judas</hi> being strangled with his grief and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, when yet no man will think that he had any repentance unto life; thus may we find an <hi>Ahab rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his clothes, putting on sackcloth upon his flesh, nay, fasting, lying in sackcloth, and going softly,</hi> 1 Kings 21 27. In so much that God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self takes notice how he humbles
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33314:19"/>himself; Others we may find <hi>howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their beds,</hi> Hos. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. and yet they are far from true Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, for it seems they did <hi>not cry unto God with their hearts;</hi> their want made them howl indeed, but not repent; for they <hi>assembled for corn and wine,</hi> and yet <hi>rebelled against God.</hi> The disgrace, and shame, and misery which the sinners wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness has brought upon him may make him truly <hi>sorrowful,</hi> when yet he is far from being truly <hi>penitent.</hi> These things may humble the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner greatly, and this Humiliation may keep off from him some <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> judgment, but will not secure him from an <hi>eternal</hi> one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are as much mistaken that take passionate resolutions of amendment for Repentance, that mistake the purpose and intention for the thing it self. We are indeed sometimes in good moods, and then we are resolved for Heaven, and for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33314:20"/>an holier life. Thus it is many times with some men, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all this are slaves to the Devil, and led captive by him at his will. Such men finde they are in great slavery, through the chains and fetters with which the Devil and their own lust hath bound them, these out of a sense of this are ready to say, <hi>Let us break their bands asunder,</hi> and <hi>cast their cords from us.</hi> These men are sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted by their sins, lashed by their consciences, terrified by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, or sometime awakened by the judgements of God that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, and then they resolve most passionately to lay by their troublesom sins, and walk in the more pleasant and more lightsom ways of Peace. How happy were it for them if they had courage and constancy enough to do what they so well resolve; But alas, these men (though they call these pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33314:20"/>by the name of repentance) return quickly to their vomit and wallowing in the mire; And then their Actions testifie to their faces they did but dissemble with God. These purposes are like the sudden resolutions that some young men take up, that have been intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the last meal, to fast the next, because their late excess has laid an uneasie load upon them, which then they find very burdensom; but when time hath wrought off the heaviness of the first excess, they forget their vow of Fasting quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; what the Apostle said of some, that they are <hi>ever learning,</hi> and yet <hi>never come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> is true of these men, they are <hi>ever repenting,</hi> and yet <hi>never arrive at true repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. They are mistaken that think every outward abstaining from the grosser acts of sin, either deserves the name of Repentance, or that it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33314:21"/>is any certain sign of it. It is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible we may abstain from some sin, and be as faulty in somthing else.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Non ego avarum</l>
                  <l>Cum veto te fieri;<note place="margin">Horat.</note> vappam ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, aut Nebulonem.</l>
               </q>
               <p>One disease may leave a man, and yet another may invade and arrest him, which is as dangerous. Men exchange one sin for another, oftner then they forsake all. And such an Exchange they judge very pardonable. They commute some one sin for some other that they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem more expedient. They leave their youthful lusts perhaps when they grow in years; but then they are slaves to Covetousness or Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, or else are overgrown with Atheism or unbelief. Men will part with some sin they can best spare, or not so well follow, and think they have well acquitted
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33314:21"/>themselves, though <hi>Agag</hi> and the fattest of the flock, their most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirable sins be spared. They will perhaps avoid the grosser enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which the World observes most, and yet be full of more refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, spiritual and mental wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. They will not <hi>kill,</hi> but yet <hi>hate</hi> their brother, or are <hi>angry with him without a cause.</hi> They do not <hi>commit adultery,</hi> but yet they allow themselves to <hi>lust.</hi> They leave that sin which either they dare not or cannot follow, and not because they hate their sin, or love their God: Some Vices they abstain from, not out of disaffection, but out of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy. Some other lust, it may be, has either more power, or more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedience; Nay, perhaps they sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice some of their lusts to the Religion they own, which they know exacts an obedience from them; It shall have some sins de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to destruction that the rest
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33314:22"/>may live; And thus men do not only abstain from some sins, that they may keep others safe, but even strive against them too; <hi>And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on these terms Satan himself</hi> (as one hath well said) <hi>will allow us to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie some sins, nay, will himself cast the first stone at them: and like a rooking Gamester purposely lose these petty stakes, that he may afterwards sweep the board.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These things I have named, are not worthy the name of Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, nor yet are they any certain or infallible signes of it; Though where there is true Repentance, there these things also are; Repentance requires this, and more then all this. It is a greater work, and makes a greater change then all the before-named particulars do amount unto; it imports no less then a relinquishing all our sins, and a turning unto God. He that truly repents puts away every evil
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33314:22"/>thing, and subdues not only his sin, but his affection to it also. He puts off the old man, and puts on the new. For Repentance imports.</p>
               <p n="1">I. A turning from our sins; <hi>A ceasing to do evil,</hi> Isa. 1.16. A leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off our evil ways, and our evil affections; That is, we may turn from all our evil, from every sin, before we can be said to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented truly, and not only leave our sin but hate it too; But that this may be the better understood we may take these following particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
               <p n="1">(1) It is a turning from our sin when we have power to commit it. Of many men it may be truly said, that their sin rather leaves them, then they that; To leave off our sin when we can follow it no longer deserves no thanks, much less the name of true Repentance. It is too true an observation of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racides, There is,</hi> says he, <hi>that is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33314:23"/>from sinning through want,</hi> chap. 20. <hi>v.</hi> 21. We want strength, or means, or an opportunity and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, oftner then we do a will to commit sin. He that follows his lust till a decrepit age, hath put out his fire; He that drinks and games till he hath spent his estate and his credit too; In a word,<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccare non desinit, quem in extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>situm recedere a cris minibus sola facit impossibilitas non voluntas. <hi>Salv. ad eccl. Cathol. lib. 1.</hi>
                  </note> he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues in his sin as long as he is able to follow it, does not forsake his sin, but his sin forsakes him. The man is the same though his strength and power be not: His <hi>actions</hi> are not what they were, but his <hi>mind</hi> is: And certainly God looks upon a man as he is in his mind and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, not as he is forced to be in his outward carriage. He is a Thief in Gods account (though he actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly steal nothing) that would not fear to steal if he were sure that his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33314:23"/>wickedness might be hid or go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished; And he is a drunkard in Gods account, that would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that excess, were it not that he wanted means, or feared the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate: Where there is true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, the forsaking our sin is matter of <hi>choice,</hi> not <hi>necessity.</hi> We do not only <hi>abstain</hi> from our sins, but we <hi>abhor</hi> them. Our <hi>affection</hi> is changed as well as our <hi>life.</hi> Some men forsake their sins, as sick men do their meat which they love, they are denied it by their Physician as very dangerous for them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they forbear and yet long for it, and would gladly have the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint taken off. Such men as these have the same desires as before, and that their actions are not the same also, is not the effect of their <hi>choice,</hi> but the result of a pressing <hi>necessity.</hi> But thus far we are hypocrites and dissemblers, not true penitents. But then that man that turns from his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33314:24"/>sin in his youth, and in his health, that wants neither power nor wealth to follow his sin, nor an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to use that power, nor yet a temptation to embrace that opportunity, and yet abstains from his sin for no other cause, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he loves God, and fears his displeasure, and hates his sin, this man truly repents; especially if he adde</p>
               <p n="2">(2) Constancy to this: some men are very angry with their sins at fits, and for a short time, but by degrees their anger cools, and they run into the embraces of their sins again: They fall out with their sins just as a fond and foolish Lover falls out with his Mystress, when yet <hi>una falsa Lachrymula,</hi> a tear or a fair invitation, a smile or sigh shall make up this breach, and the man is then as fond and as foolish, as much a slave and servant as he was before. We are in little feuds
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33314:24"/>and bickerings against our sins, but they rise to no height, and continue no time. 'Tis our continuing in well-doing that speaks our repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to be compleat. Many men are ready to think themselves free, who yet draw their chain after them, and are easily overcome by <hi>Sin in fair Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Heb. 12.1. When their sin comes to them well arraied and attired, when it courts them, and importunately wooes them, when it comes to them, as <hi>Jael</hi> did to <hi>Slsera,</hi> with a <hi>Turn in, my Lord, turn into me, fear not,</hi> Judg. 4.18. when it comes to the sinner like the strange woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.3. whose <hi>lips drop as an Honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb,</hi> and <hi>her Mouth smoother then Oyle;</hi> And makes an earnest prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of pleasure and profit, an <hi>all All this I'le give thee;</hi> then the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner falls into the embraces of his sins again, and becomes a vassal
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33314:25"/>and a slave again, and his love to his sin is, after his little quarrels with it, redintegrated and made strong: Such mens affections to their sins were never throughly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued and mortified, their repentance was never perfect and compleat. <hi>Know ye not</hi> (says the Apostle) <hi>that to whom ye yield your selves servants to obey, his servants ye are to whom ye obey; whether of sin unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness,</hi> Rom. 6.16. Not that I would be so under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, but that a man that hath tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repented may fall into some sins again, through infirmity or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, through sudd en surreption or surprise, and sometime through negligence and want of due care and watchfulness. But then</p>
               <p n="3">(3) This is against the constant bent and meaning, the biass and inclination of the man: 'Tis that which he constantly and earnestly desires to avoid and shun: He looks
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33314:25"/>upon it as his great misery and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happiness; And</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) He rifes again by a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, by an hearty and godly sorrow; if <hi>Peter deny his Master,</hi> we soon find that he goes out and <hi>weeps bitterly;</hi> if such a man miss his way, yet he turns back again, and renews his pace, and doubles his diligence, and returns home to his father again, and this leads me to the second part of Repentance, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. A turning to God: <hi>I will go to my father,</hi> says the Prodigal son; and this may be called <hi>Conversion:</hi> But that we may the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what is implied in this, we may take the import of it in the following Severals. Now this turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God does comprehend in it and suppose together</p>
               <p n="1">(I) A due sight and sense of the danger and misery of our present condition that we are in, and here
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33314:26"/>it begins. The sinner begins to consider now what he does, and whither he is going; he begins to discern his danger and misery. He is like a man newly awakened out of a deep sleep, when the house a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him is on fire, when the Buil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing trembles, and the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borhood cries out, and the flames begin to threaten him, and the man sees that danger which his sleep but now hid from his eyes. He sees himself now upon the very brink of Hell, and very near be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing devoured and swallowed up by those unquenchable flames. A sire from Heaven he sees is falling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Sodom,</hi> and the Avenger of blood he sees is following him, and his soul is in great distress for a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Refuge to flie unto. He is like a traveller in a foreign land, that hath wandred securely from his right way, and is strayed into paths of very great hazard and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33314:26"/>which makes him doubtful and at a stand. His heart mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gives him, and he now begins to consider with himself whither his way will lead him: He suspects his way too broad, and too much beaten to be that way that leads to life: He remembers now that he hath heard his Saviour say, that the way is narrow and strait that leads to life, and that there be but few that find it: And he now remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that God hath told him that the paths that he treads in will bring him unto death. He remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that, that it is plainly said, that <hi>without Holiness no man shall see God,</hi> Heb. 12.14. And then he considers what a sad portion of things abides for him, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able he is to lie down in everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burnings, and to lose the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God for ever, whose fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour is better then life it self: He knows there is but a very little
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33314:27"/>distance between him and eternal destruction, and that if God take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his life he is undone for ever, and that nothing in this world can countervail so great a loss as the favour of God, and the eternal wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his foul. Thus does the Convert begin his Conversion: Thus the Psalmist did, <hi>I thought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ways,</hi> (says he) <hi>and turned my feet unto thy Testimonies,</hi> Psal. 119.59. And the Prodigal son did thus also, he made this the first step towards his amendment, for of him the first good tidings, and hopeful presage we meet with is that which we read, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17. <hi>When he came to himself, he said, how many hired servants of my fathers have bread e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and to spare, and I perish with hunger?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2) A firm resolution of turning to God. <hi>I will arise and go to my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> says the Prodigal son: And this resolution the true Penitent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33314:27"/>does not take up lightly and rashly neither, as many do that soon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent them of their repentance, but upon mature consideration he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved for God and Heaven what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it cost him; though he pluck out his right eye, and cut off his right hand: That is, though he part with his most beloved sins: He will have the Pearl though he sell all he have, and endure great hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to obtain it. He is willing to accept of Jesus Christ as his Lord and Master, as well as his Priest and Saviour; that is, he is as willing to be ruled by Christ as to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by him. He resolves to obey his Saviour, and to follow him through all difficulties and dangers. He will not leave him though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do; though his Friends and Relatives, the wife of his Bosom, or the son of his strength forsake him, and serve other Gods: Just as it was with <hi>Ruth,</hi> so is it with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33314:28"/>the true Penitent. She would not leave <hi>Naomi,</hi> though she not only bid her turn back, and discouraged her besides, and though her Sister <hi>Orpah</hi> returned unto her people, and to her Gods. But she tells her, <hi>Whither thou goest I will go, and where thou lodgest I will lodge; thy people shall be my people, and thy God my God; where thou diest I will die, and there will I be buried,</hi> Ruth 1.11, 12. He that repents does so, he will follow Christ whither ever he shall lead him, to a Cross, or to a Stake, to a barren wilderness, or to a place of Skulls, through affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and tribulations. He will part with father and mother, and wife and children, and brethren and sisters, and life it self rather then not be his disciple, <hi>Luke</hi> 14 26, 33. For he considers, like a wise Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that this undertaking may cost him no less then all this. There are indeed but few such. Converts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33314:28"/>as these, I fear; yet do none de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the name that do not do this? Many indeed partake of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptism of Christ; receive of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood, that will do nothing for him. There are many that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him for the loaves, that will not follow him to the Cross: they will cleave to Christ while he feeds them, but when he commands their estates or lives, they, like the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darens,</hi> for loss of an herd of Swine, desire him to depart out of their Coasts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.34. or they do as the Ruler in the Gospel did, who when our Saviour told him he must sell all and give to the poor, <hi>He went away sorrowful, for he was very rich,</hi> Luke 18.23. But the true Convert counts all but dross that he may gain Christ, and he is so far convinced of his misery, without the mercy of God and light of his Countenance, that he is willing to accept of this mercy upon: any
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33314:29"/>terms: And therefore he resolves to turn to God without any reservs whatever: He sets before his eyes all the difficulties and discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he may meet with, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solves with Gods strength to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go them all that he may obtain the prize.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) And actual and entire resigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a mans self unto God: And this is that which perfects and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleats our Repentance. When we come to give God our hearts, which we formerly set upon the World, and upon oursins, then have we tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repented, and not till then. For he that hath truly repented becomes a new man, he hath bid an everlasting farewel to all his evil ways, to all his old familiars in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and is now transplanted and engraffed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a new Family: and when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members his former evil ways, it is with tears in his eyes, or true sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in his heart, when he thinks
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33314:29"/>how foolish he hath been. Now he hath left his former customs, company and pleasures: He is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into a new Family, he hath contracted a new Kindred and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latives: He obeys another Master, and is ruled by other Laws, and is conducted by a better spirit, and hath vowed obedience to another and a better Lord: His Convenants are sealed, and he hath bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self by all that is sacred or great to an universal obedience, and he cannot return or draw back with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a strange destruction. He is not the same man which he was, other Lords have had dominion over him, he hath been enslaved by his vile affections and lusts, but he is now made free by the Son of God, and he that was before a slave of sin is now a Servant of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. In a word, <hi>All old things are done away, and all things are become new.</hi> There is a very great
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33314:30"/>and remarkable change passed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Upon his minde and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing: For God works upon the understanding first, and does in this new creature use the same me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, which he did when he cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the World at first, where we find that light was the work of the first day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3. before that light was made there was a great dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness upon the face of the deep, till God by the light he made had cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it away. It is just so with the natural and unregenerate man, he is in a very great darkness till the eyes of his minde are opened: And the Apostle seems to tell us that God makes a <hi>new</hi> creature after the same manner that he made the <hi>old,</hi> in these words: <hi>For God who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the light to shine out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, hath shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jesus Christ,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33314:30"/>2 Cor. 4.6. Our blessed Saviour, who is the <hi>true light,</hi> Joh. 1.9. Came into the world, <hi>to give light to them that sit in darkness, and in the shadow of death, and to guide our feet in to the way of Peace,</hi> Luke 1.79. While the sinner goes on in his evil way he walks in darkness: <hi>The God of this World blinds his minde, lest the light of the glorious Gospel of Christ who is the Image of God, should shine unto him,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.4. <hi>Ye were som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times darkness</hi> (says the Apostle to his <hi>Ephesians</hi>) <hi>but now are ye light in the Lord,</hi> Eph. 5.8. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was somtimes darkness also, <hi>I verily thought with my self, that I ought to do many things contrary to the Name of Jesus of</hi> Nazareth, Act. 26.9. But it pleased God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten him from Heaven with a light greater then that of the Sun, and then he becomes a Minister of that which before he persecuted, and is sent to open mens eyes, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33314:31"/>to turn them from darkness to light, and from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan unto God, <hi>v.</hi> 18. And so it is with every man that is converted from his evil ways to God; A great light breaks in upon his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing: His mind before was darkned, and he is now like a man that comes out of a dark dungeon, or like one that never saw before, or never saw distinctly and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: But now the scales are fallen off his eyes, the veil is removed, and he is restored to sight. He sees now that his sin is no small matter, and that he is of all fools the most deplorable that makes a mock of sin: He sees that all wickness is folly, and that the fear of the Lord is the greatest wisdom: He sees that the Gospel is a great truth, and that he that preaches it hath all the reason in the World to be very earnest and importunate: he sees that Hell is no Fable, but the most
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33314:31"/>necessary and unavoidable Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of a wicked life. Now he sees that God will by no means clear the guilty, and that he is not so merciful as to forget to be just: He sees now how wofully the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil abused him, in leading him aside into the ways of sin, and miscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of God and of Religion. He sees that he hath been a fool, and walked always upon the borders of Hell, and had not the mercy of God laid hold of him, he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver seen it till it had been too late. In a word, he sees that he hath <hi>no fruit in those things whereof he is now ashamed, for the end of those things is death,</hi> Rom. 6.21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Upon his will and heart: the bent and inclination of that is much changed and altered; His heart is now right in the sight of God: He had no savour or relish of the things of God that stay'd with him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; So that when he prayed with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33314:32"/>his lips, his heart stay'd behind: and though he had many notices of things swimming in his head, yet he had no relish of them in his heart: His good principles were weak and ineffectual, and he lived as altogether unconcerned in them: He could indeed before this great change was wrought, acknowledge God the Fountain of all goodness, and the root from whom every good thing did spring; yet then he did not live as if this were true, but still loved his sin and pleasure more then his God. But now he tasts and sees that the Lord is gracious, and what service he performs to God, he does it heartily: When he prayed to God before, he was like some Clock that strikes right indeed, but yet the hand of it points amiss, and not at the same houre that its striking gave you warning of: He prayed before as to the matter of his Petitions very uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33314:32"/>and agreeably, but his heart was not right in the sight of God, that pointed at somthing else, and at somthing short of what his words did import.<note place="margin">Aug. Conf. l <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> Thus St. <hi>Austin</hi> confesses of himself that he was wont to pray to God <hi>to give him Chastity and Continence,</hi> (and that was a good hearing) but then his heart staid behind with a <hi>not yet Lord,</hi> his heart did not point so forward; for he confesses, that when he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus, he was afraid that God should hear him speedily. St. <hi>Paul</hi> prayed doubtless before his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, for he was a very strict. Pharisee, but he did not pray as he did after God had brought him home to himself; when the Lord tells <hi>Ananias</hi> of his praying; with a <hi>Behold he prays,</hi> Act. 9.11. The sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner prays perhaps for the same thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gs that the true Convert does, but not so earnestly and so hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33314:33"/>He prays for the holy Spirit as a very hungry man prays for bread; when he begs Wisdom of God, <hi>He seeks her as Silver, and searches for her as for hid treasures,</hi> Prov. 2.4. In a word, he does not only perform an outward worship to God, but he loves him with all his heart, and is inwardly delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his service.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Upon his whole life also. He lived after the guise and fashion of the World before: He hath now left his old wonts, his sin and his evil company. He talks of other matters, he thinks of other things, and is delighted with other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: He that before delighted in nothing but Merchandise, or Farms and Leases, and Yokes of Oxen, in Mirth and jolly Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; in Chambering and Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; Honour and Greatness, now delights in God, and in his Gospel: And do really value a <hi>Promise</hi> above
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33314:33"/>a great <hi>Lease</hi> or <hi>Bond:</hi> and is more afraid of <hi>Gods displeasure</hi> then of a <hi>Famine</hi> or <hi>Plague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I have shewed what true Repentance does imply: He that would enter into Heaven must thus be changed: No less then all this is indispensibly required of us; which is a great work, and requires much strength and some time; and therefore to put it into so narrow a Compass as the remainder of our lives when we lie a dying, is most unreasonable. Repentance is not so <hi>easie</hi> and <hi>short</hi> a work as to be put off to that moment, when we have not only the <hi>least time,</hi> but the <hi>least strength</hi> also. And yet of all men's in the World, their Repentance will require the greatest <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>time,</hi> who, having always lived in sin, have the sins and evil habits of an whole life to unrawel and undo. And thus much of my first Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:33314:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>Now this will farther appear to be a very great mistake, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that an holy life is not only necessary to a comfortable death, but also to an happy Eternity: And if an holy life must go before an happy and glorious Resurrection, what shall we think of them that lead a wicked life, and yet think hereafter to live with God in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Now that an holy life, and an universal inherent holiness of our Nature, is indispensibly necessary to our eternal happiness hereafter, will abundantly appear from these following Severals.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The holy Scriptures do very frequently and plainly teach us this Lesson. This is the constant language of them, which they speak all along. And the man that doubts
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33314:34"/>of the truth of this, or else is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of it, it is either because he does not read the Scriptures, or will not believe them: For though the holy Scriptures be in many things hard to be understood, and there be difficulties in them too great for the wisest Clerk, and many other things of less moment in which learned and religious men cannot yet agree: Yet notwithstanding all this, when they tell us the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of an holy life, they do it so plainly, that he that runs may read it, and there is not the least place left for dispute or controversie in this matter. This is that in which all Dissenters in other things do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and agree; And that which may, without any learning or great scholarship, be very easily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood. For in this matter they give out a certain and distinct sound that every man may prepare himself to battel. They tell us that, <hi>without
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33314:35"/>holiness no Man shall see God,</hi> Heb. 12.14. That, <hi>if we live after the flesh we shall die,</hi> Rom. 8.13. And that <hi>we must be holy in all manner of conversation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.15. They tell us plainly, that <hi>except a man be born again, he cannot see into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God,</hi> John 3.3. Besides, they teach us that this World we now live in, is a <hi>Field,</hi> and intimate to us that our present time is a <hi>Seeds-time,</hi> and they tell us moreover, <hi>that whatsoever a man sows, that he shall also reap, that if me some to the flesh, we shall of the flesh reap corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi> Gal. 6.7. That is, our harvest shall be according to our seed so that if our <hi>works</hi> be <hi>evil,</hi> our <hi>doom</hi> must needs be <hi>sad.</hi> Besides this, they tell us distinctly and severally, what those evil seeds are that we must beware of, what those evil works are that will bring us to an eternal destruction, <hi>viz. Adultery, Fornication, Uncleanness, Lascivious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33314:35"/>Idolatry, Witchcraft, Hatred, Variance, Enialations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Heresies, Envyings, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Drunkenness, Revellings, and such like,</hi> Gal. 5.19. Nay, the Word of God gives us in several Catalogues and Rolls of those sins that will keep us out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, that we might be sure to avoid them, as appears in the places following, which will deserve our very serious perusal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5. And not only so, but it also calls upon us loudly to beware, lest by any means we be deceived, it being as much as our souls are worth: It bids beware, <hi>Be not deceived,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9. And again, <hi>Let no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you with vain words, for because of these things comes the wrath of God upon the Children of disobedience,</hi> Eph. 5.6. And again the same A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle cries out aloud, <hi>For these things sake, the wrath of God comes
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33314:36"/>upon the children of disobedience,</hi> Col. 3.6. And again, the same Apostle having reckoned up the works of the flesh, earnestly cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s out, <hi>Of the which</hi> (says h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) <hi>I tell you before, as I have also told you in time past, that they which'd such things shall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berit the Kingdom of God,</hi> Gal. 5.21. And again, <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked,</hi> Gal. 6.7. In which expressions so often repeated, and so earnestly recommended, and so plainly delivered, the Apostle shews an extraordinary <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and a very great care of the souls of men at once. Whatever we are mistaken in, he would not have us so great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mistaken, as to think there is no absolute necessity of an holy life in order to our happiness hereafter: For there cannot be a more great and dangerous error, then to think we may live as we lift, and yet be happy with God hereafter. Now the Holy Scripture, that it might
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33314:36"/>beat all men off from this mistake does moreover inform us, that <hi>God is no Kespecter of persons,</hi> Acts 10.34. And that be our Priviledges and Prerogatives what they will, yet shall none of them supersede the necessity of an holy life. <hi>For in Christ Jesus, neither Circumcision availeth any thing, nor uncircumcisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but faith, which worketh by love.</hi> Gal. 5.9. Rom. 2.11.25. That we That we are baptized into the Christian faith, and continue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the pale of the visible Church, that we descend from never so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Parents, and partake of all the Ministe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of the Church, that we profess our selves of the strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Sect, and that we have a very great discerning in the Laws of God. All this, and more then all this, will do us no good at last (but rather inhance our condemnation) if we lead wicked lives. Though we have a <hi>Levite</hi> for our <hi>Priest,</hi> and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33314:37"/>never so <hi>Orthodox</hi> a <hi>faith,</hi> yet if lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the mean time we have an <hi>Idol</hi> for our <hi>God,</hi> and our <hi>manners</hi> be <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane,</hi> we are still in the way that leads down to the Chambers of death. Nay, though we say un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Christ, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> and though we could truly say unto him at that day, that <hi>we had prophecied in his Name, and done many wonderful works.</hi> Mat. 7.22. yet he will not regard us, whoever we be, and whatever we have done for him, if we have been <hi>workers of iniquity.</hi> Nay, he would not regard us though we were of his Kindred, of the same line age and blood, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 49, 50.) though we were his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or Sisters, or Mother after the flesh. If his own Mother had not believed on him as well as born him, she had been a miserable wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. For she was more happy in being his <hi>disciple,</hi> then in being his <hi>Mother.</hi> Nay, and our Saviour
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33314:37"/>himself seems to intimate no less, when after a certain woman had cried out, <hi>Blessed is the Womb that bare thee, and the Paps which thou hast sucked:</hi> He said, <hi>Yea rather, Blessed are they that hear the Word of God and keep it,</hi> Luke 11.27, 28. No less then this did God require in the old Law, and in comparison with this those sacrifices and rights of his own appointment were not accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him: For even then a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart was unto God the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Sacrifice; a slaying of their sins was more pleasing to him then the blood of thousands of Bullocks: Sincere Prayer was then the chois<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est incense, and the paring away their proud and callous flesh was that Circumcision that God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lghted in, <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.8.51.16.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.20.7.22, 23. <hi>Esa.</hi> 1.11, 12. <hi>Micah</hi> 6.6, 7, 8. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.22. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hough God required sacrifices and other ceremonies, yet if they offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33314:38"/>up the beast, and spared their sin, that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Beast with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, they were not welcom to Gods Altars. If they cut off the fore-skin of their flesh, and let their hearts in the mean time be overgrown with their pride and unbelief, if they offered incense up towards Heaven, and kept their hearts below upon the lusts of the flesh, God was not pleased with such a service, though of his own appointment. Thus he tells the Jews, <hi>He that killeth an Oxe</hi> (<note n="*" place="margin">So the LXXII. render it, O <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and in the mean time spares his sin) <hi>is as if he slew a man: He that sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth a Lamb, is as if he cut off a dogs neck: He that offereth an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is as if he had offered Swines blood: He that burneth Incense as if he blessed an Idol,</hi> Esa. 66.3. Such Sacrifices of fools were but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. They fed the fire upon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33314:38"/>the Altar, but they made no atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. God abhorred such servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as these, for with him <hi>to obey is better then sacrifice, and to hearken then the fat of Lambs,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.22. Now if under the Law God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an holy life, then under the Gospel nothing can excuse us from it. And thus much the Apostle teaches us in these words; <hi>Sin shall not have dominion over you; for ye are not under the Law but under grace,</hi> Rom. 6.14. After all this, one would think, that he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siders these things, and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves them, should no longer doubt of the necessity of an holy life, and therefore should not dare to go on in his sin, and think on his death-bed, to make an amends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> he miscarriage of a wicked life, with a few good words of course. Certainly, in other things there is nothing truer, then that the faults and defectiveness of any
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33314:39"/>of the premises, are constantly found also in the Conclusion: And if it be true in this case (as the Word of God assures us it is) no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more absurd, then to expect so good a <hi>Conclusion,</hi> as <hi>a glorious Resurrection,</hi> from the <hi>faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty premises</hi> of a <hi>wicked life.</hi> And we shall judge very strangely, if we think a few good words of a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sinner, will avail as much with God as an holy life; we cannot say he lived a good life, that never called upon God till he lay a dying. The <hi>parts</hi> of our life must be holy,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> before the <hi>whole</hi> can be called so: We do not call a Picture of Statue fair, that hath not all its parts and proportions. I shall end this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular with the words of a very worthy Divine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Papists:<note place="margin">Mr. Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</note> His words are these, <hi>If I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33314:39"/>follow the Scripture, I must not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise my self Salvation, without effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual dereliction and mortification of all Vices, and the effectual Practice of all Christian Vertues. But your Church opens an easier and broader way to Heaven; and though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue all my life long in a course of sin, and without the Practice of any Vertue, yet gives me assurance that I may be let into Heaven at a Postern gate, even by any Act of Attrition at the houre of death, if it be joyned with confession, or by an Act of Contrition without Confession.</hi> Thus he to my present purpose.</item>
                  <item>2. But if we adde to this, the infinite and essential holiness of Gods Nature, we cannot imagine that he should receive the unclean and filthy sinner into his Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
<q>
                        <l>—Quid enim sperare nocentibus aegris</l>
                        <l>Concessum? ant quae non dignior hostia vita?</l>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:33314:40"/>Who can believe that God, who hates sin with a perfect hatred, and cannot endure it in his sight; <hi>That is light, and in whom is no darkness at all,</hi> that cast the Angles out of Heaven for their pride, and our first Parents out of Paradise for their Rebellion, that drowned the old World for their ungodliness, and burnt up <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> for their wicked lives, and hath ever destroyed the Nations for their sins, should yet entertain the sinner into his love, receive him into his arms, shine upon him with his favour, and rejoyce over him to do him good: Or that He, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom all things are naked and open, should be so easily deceived, as to be charmed with a parcel of good words from a dying man, who in the mean time is an enemy to him in his heart. We know such a mans <hi>sacrifice is an abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 15.8. <hi>And we know God heareth not sinners,</hi> John 9.31.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33314:40"/>Nay, the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could say,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Hierocles in Carm Pytha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                     <hi>That an unclean person might not have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with a pure Being.</hi> We may as well expect that all the Elements should change their natures, that the fire should become cold and tame, and the Waters dry and hard; that an excess of light, and a thick drakness should amicably agree and sit down together at the same time and place, that contradictions should be at no distance, or that God should cease to be what he is; As that God who is holy, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwise, who hates sin perfectly, and cannot choose but hate it wheresoever it is, should be at perfect friendship and favour with that man, that loves his sin heartily, and embraces it with great delight. We deceive our selves infinitely if we think he will or can, for it is contrary to his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33314:41"/>Indeed if the God whom we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vidae.</hi> Cic. de natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Deor. l. <hi>2.</hi> Plut in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n. Periclis. Prudent. cont Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. l. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> were no better then the Heathen gods were reported to be, of whose <hi>quarrels, adulteries, murders and feuds,</hi> we read in the Writings of their own Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, then might any man soon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a fit Companion of such a Deity: Adulterers, Drunkards, Thievs and Robbers would be very fit mates for such false gods as <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Bacchus, Mercery,</hi> and such like, which were some of those whom the Heathens worshipped. For, <hi>to imitate him whom we worship,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jamblich de vita Pythag c. <hi>28.</hi>
                     </note> hath always bin thought safe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; And he was one of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest Heathens that said, <hi>That those men did ridiculously, that sought for that which is truly righteous from any other but the gods, or those that were like them.</hi> And he adds
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33314:41"/>very well, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>That we must do those things with which God is delighted.</hi> Nor could there be a surer rule then this, had they not bin mistaken in the object of their Worship: And it is likely the Heathen were the more wicked upon this score:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Semina pene omnium scelerum a Diis suis pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantium turba colleg<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t.</hi> Jui Fi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mich. de errore Profan. Relig. Vide Lactant. Inst. l. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. c. 10</note> and if they were, they were not reproveable from their own principles. For why should <hi>Cicero</hi> inveigh against <hi>Verres</hi> for committing adultery; when <hi>Jove</hi> himself whom they worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, had done the same; or against <hi>P. Clodius</hi> for Incest, when their great Deity was known to have been incestuous.<note place="margin">Aug. co nf. l. 1 c. 16.</note> St. <hi>Austin</hi> takes notice of the leud young man in the <hi>Comedian;</hi> that justified him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in his uncleanness by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33314:42"/>of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and did as it were animate and provoke himself to lust, <hi>quasi coelesti Magisterio,</hi> by the warranty of <hi>Jove.</hi> No better could be expected from those that worshipped such De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities, and believed such things of them:<note place="margin">Lactant. Inst, l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> Who could expect any thing but cruelty from the Worshippers of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Bellona?</hi> or any reverence to Parents from the worshippers of <hi>Jupiter?</hi> who would look for cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stity from the Adorers of an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teress, or for Justice from them that served a Thievish <hi>Mercury:</hi> They were not like to be chaste or sober that offered sacrifice to <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> and those other false gods, whose adulteries and excesses were not only reported in the Writings of their followers, but represented upon open Theatres, that all men might know them. But our God, whom we worship, is an Holy God,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33314:42"/>and we must be so also if we would worship him aright, or be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him. And this is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that God himself uses with us, and very forcible it is, to be holy because he is so. <hi>It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> (says the Apostle) <hi>be ye holy, for I am holy,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.16. And indeed we often find this written in the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> where the Jews are required to be holy because God is so, <hi>Levit.</hi> 11.44.19.2.20.7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.17. And therefore we may not expect any favour from God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less we become like him.</item>
                  <item>3. The necessity of an holy life here in order to our future happiness will farther appear, if we consider the nature of that happiness, or Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which God hath reserved for us: There is no one thing in which men more mistake, I fear, then in their conceits about Heaven: Men speaks of it much, and every man seems to desire it as a good place,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33314:43"/>or state in general, when in the mean time they know not what it is, nor wherein it does consist. We are very desirous of Heaven, but not careful to fit and prepare our selves for it, The Mother of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedees</hi> Children would have her two sons sit by Christ in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but yet does not beg for them the grace that should enable them to drink the Cup, and receive the Baptism that should prepare them for it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. Men conceive of it after a carnal and fleshly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Pembles</hi> Sermon of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co ance.</note> Thus did he that thought it a <hi>Green Medow.</hi> Thus that great Impostor <hi>Mahomet</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises his true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise watered with delightful Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Amyrald</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions <hi>part</hi> 3 <hi>ch</hi> 3. Vide Mr. <hi>Greaves</hi> his Description of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio.</hi> ch. 11.</note> adorned with stately Trees, and enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with variety of fruits. Where
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33314:43"/>men shall be magnificently cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and stretch themselves upon costly beds, and be attended with delicate musick, and have Wives transcendently beautiful: Such a Paradise did that Beast promise his disciples: which is a clear Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the man was immersed in sensual delights, and unworthy of the reasonable soul. Much such a state do the poor carnal Jews dream, that their <hi>Messias</hi> shall bring them to when he comes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid.</hi> Chald Paraph <hi>in</hi> Cant <hi>8.2. Vide</hi> Bua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Synag. Judaic. c. <hi>36.</hi>
                     </note> when they shall be feasted with great Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and drink of the wine of Paradise, that hath bin reserved for from the days of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> At this Feast they name the very dishes that shall be provided, and what sports shall go before, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such conceits are men ready to have of Heaven: And indeed, if. Heaven were such a place as this
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33314:44"/>kind of men speak of, it would much please a prophane man, and the most wicked would at all times be very fit for Heaven. The Drunkard and the Glutton, the proud and ambitious, the worldling and effeminate would be well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with such a <hi>Fools Baradise</hi> as this; And there would be no man, though never so much depraved, but would be very fit for such a sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sual happiness. But we are taught to think otherwise of Heaven, that there is <hi>no marrying, or giving in marriage there,</hi> Luke 20.35. And that <hi>no unclean thing shall enter into it,</hi> Rev. 20.27. And therefore as we would be happy, so we must be holy: For holiness is not only ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary by <hi>a necessity of Precept,</hi> but by <hi>a necessity of means.</hi> For as wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness does lay a foundation for our misery, and a train for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction,<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Smith</hi>'s Select Discourses <hi>p</hi> 446.</note> every sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33314:44"/>being within <hi>the attractive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Hell: Sin and Hell</hi> being of the same lineage, and always twist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together: So also is <hi>holiness</hi> of absolute and indispensible necessity to our future <hi>happiness:</hi> They being rather two several notions of one thing, then things in themselves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct. And therefore no man may promise himself Heaven here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that does not live an holy life here. We are here in a state of trial and probation, and as it were at School in a lower form, where if we improve our time well, and do our tasks, that is, if we mortifie and subdue our evil affections, then we shall be removed to an higher forme, and added <hi>to the spirits of just men made perfect.</hi> But if we trifle away our time, or spend it amiss, we shall be <hi>thrown down among Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites and unbelievers.</hi> Nor can it be otherwise then thus. For what should a wicked man do in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33314:45"/>Heaven; Certainly, such a state would be a torment to him if the thing were possible. In stead of being his <hi>happiness,</hi> it would be his <hi>prison.</hi> He would be weary of that state, which now he seems so much to defire. What pleasure would he find in singing perpetual praises to God, that is now weary of giving him thanks! What con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent would the covetous Worldling find in Heaven! There he will find no Leases or Farms for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase, no widows or fatherless to oppress, no poor mens faces to grind, nor bargains to drive, nor money to put out, nor forfeitures to receive. The voluptuous man would find little pleasure there where is <hi>no marrying</hi> or <hi>giving in marriage,</hi> no beds of Ivory, nor meat or drink, nor Tavern or Alehouse, or jolly companion to carowse and quaffe withal. The proud man would take little delight in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33314:45"/>ascribing all honour and praise to God: Such men as these are not fit for <hi>Glory,</hi> who are so far from <hi>Grace.</hi> They must lie down with the devil and his Angels, they are not fit for God, and that inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among them that are san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I might adde to what I have said, this also; That it is nothing but <hi>Sin,</hi> and the want of an <hi>holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that makes the <hi>Devil</hi> so <hi>ugly.</hi> and so deplorably <hi>miserable</hi> as he is, nothing but this obstructs his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness. We all look upon the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> as a most odious, and filthy, and miserable creature: He hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally with us a very ill name, and that very justly also: But we do not consider what hath made the devil so ugly and so wretched: Now that is nothing but his sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God. For God did not make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im so, when he came out of Gods Hands he was an holy Angel,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33314:46"/>bright and spotless: But fince that his sin hath discoloured him, and left those filthy spots upon his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which if they could again be separated from him, he would clear up into an Angel of light, and be better then the best of us. But his Sin hath <hi>stained</hi> him, and <hi>stigmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi> him now, and hath made him at once the most <hi>deformed</hi> and most <hi>miserable</hi> creature. And that man, whoever he be that lives in sin and loves it, that does the works of the <hi>Devil, i. e.</hi> that is a liar, a false Accuser of Gods children, an. Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to the souls of men, that is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, envious and proud, such a man is ugly and miserable as the devil is. For, to say no more but the very truth, such a man is a <hi>Devil Incarnate:</hi> He differs only in <hi>name</hi> from him, while he hath the very same <hi>nature:</hi> And while he lives in these sins, the Devi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himself may belong to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33314:46"/>of Heaven as much as he: For who can believe that a <hi>man</hi> should be <hi>happy</hi> with those very sins about him, which at the same time make the <hi>Devil</hi> unavoidably <hi>miserable:</hi> Or that <hi>we</hi> should ever enter <hi>into Heaven</hi> with those very sins, which cast the <hi>Devil out thence;</hi> Did not God spare the <hi>Angels</hi> that sinned, but cast them down to Hell, (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4.) And shall he spare <hi>man,</hi> and make him happy also, though he have the very same sins deeply root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his nature! It cannot be: It is true indeed, such a man as this may lay aside his sins, and obtain mercy at the hands of God through Jesus Christ; but if he do not this, the sins that make the <hi>Devil</hi> so vile in the eyes of God, and so mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, will make <hi>him</hi> so likewise. And therefore when a wicked man pretends to defie the Devil, and professes to hate him, he ought to consider that these are but very
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33314:47"/>vain words, when at the same time he embraces his works. For we are obliged by our Profession of Christianity, as well as by our first Promise, <hi>to renounce the devil and all his works.</hi> And if we defie his <hi>name</hi> only, and do not renounce his <hi>works,</hi> we do but like the Coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Souldier</hi> that <hi>exclaims</hi> against his enemie whom he will not <hi>fight.</hi> It was an excellent saying of <hi>Sir aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, When the ungodly curseth Satan, he curseth his own soul,</hi> Eccl. 21.27. When a wicked man curseth the devil, and is at the same time one of his children and followers, he does but curse himself.</p>
               <p>If then we will believe the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> rather then the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a <hi>corrupt Church;</hi> and think that <hi>God</hi> is necessarily <hi>holy,</hi> and not such an one as the <hi>Heathens</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped; and that <hi>Heaven</hi> is an <hi>holy</hi> State, and not a <hi>Paradice</hi> for <hi>fools</hi> and <hi>sensualists;</hi> we must also
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33314:47"/>grant, that <hi>holiness here</hi> is of abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute necessity to our <hi>happiness here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> And then certainly, this shews us again the vanity of those men that lead wicked lives, and live without God in the world, and think to make amends for all with a few good words at last (which they call Repentance) and by that means to get into a better world then this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>I shall now shew the very great danger of delaying our repentance to the latter end of our days: What very great, <hi>hazards,</hi> and <hi>uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and <hi>peradventures</hi> we run when we do so.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is uncertain how long we shall live, and therefore there is danger in putting off our Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to our old age. God never
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33314:48"/>gave us our life in <hi>Lease</hi> for <hi>Years;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Natura dedit usura vitae tanquam pecuniae nulla praestituta die. <hi>Cic. so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c. qu. l. 1.</hi>
                  </note> we are but <hi>Tenants</hi> at the Will of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and he may throw us out of our <hi>Cottages</hi> when he pleases. We have no day granted us to pay back the lives that God hath lent us, they may at any time be required of us. It was the Devils first lie, and he is always repeating it, <hi>Ye shall not surely die,</hi> Gen. 3.4. And if he can by this means rock us asleep he hath us fast enough. But yet we have dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience how vain a thing a man at his best estate is, and how extremely vain it is to promise our selves any long continuance, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign any great matters here. The Jews have a good Ptoverb, that <hi>Many old Camels carry the skins of the younger Camels</hi> to the Market.<note place="margin">Vide Bux<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril. Hebr.</note> And indeed one would think that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33314:48"/>the sudden death of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, of our Friends and Relatives, that were younger, and stronger, and better then we, should convince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that we have no assurance that we shall live long. How many have we known or heard of, upon whom death came, and gave no warning: For so many times it is, men die suddenly when they least think of such a thing. Many a man dies in the midst of a journey, in a crowd and throng of worldly business, when they are just arrived to their preferment and the summe of their hopes, upon their marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age or their new honours, in their meals or sports, in a drunken fit or quarrel, and when they thought least of such a thing;<note place="margin">Tu oceupatus es, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta festi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at: Mors interim aderit c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> velis no is vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum esi. <hi>Sen, de brev. vit. c. 8.</hi>
                  </note> then hath death o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken them, and laid on them its cold hands, closed their eyes, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33314:49"/>stopped their breath, and spoiled their designes, and put an end to their mirth, and caused all their thoughts to perish. And then the man that had not time to serve God, must find time to die, and he that had not leisure to amend his life, must now lose it against his will. We often hear such tidings as this, that such a man is suddenly dead, whom we saw a little before in perfect health, and heard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving some great things he would do ere long. And indeed there is no reason we should wonder at any of these things; for, besides that such things are very common, it is more to be marvelled at that we should live so long then that we should die so suddenly. For how very easily is this earthen vessel broken, in what great danger are we every day! Too great an <hi>heal,</hi> or too much <hi>cold;</hi> too much <hi>sleep,</hi> or too great <hi>watching;</hi> if we either
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33314:49"/>
                  <hi>eat</hi> too much, or <hi>abstain</hi> too long; or else <hi>labour</hi> too hard, we are soon destroyed: And if we presume upon our own temperance, yet who can secure himself from enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: A wilde beast may meet him, and tear him in pieces, 2 <hi>King:</hi> 2.24. Or an enemy may give him a thrust under the fifth rib, (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.27.) and let out his soul that way, or a fool or a Mad-man may strike him to the wall when an evil spirit is upon him: Thou mayst enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an house that may fall upon thee and kill thee, (<hi>Luke</hi> 13.4.) Or thy horse may throw thee out of this into another world; thou mayst catch the Plague, or be surprized in thy games, or choaked in thy meals. The rage of a Tyrant, the infection of a disease, the poison of a morsel or a draught, a Clap of Thunder, or a flash of Lightning may quickly send thee to thy long home; <hi>The Lord may smite thee,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33314:50"/>or thy day may come to die, or thou mayst descend into battel and perish,</hi> 1 Sam. 26.10. Thy life is in Gods hand, who may take it away when he pleaseth, or whensoever thou displeasest him. And then if thou die in thy <hi>sin,</hi> thou must lie down in <hi>sorrow,</hi> and dwell with <hi>everlasting burnings.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">R. Eleazar.</note> And therefore it was wholesome advice the Jew gave his Scholar, that <hi>he should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent one day before he died:</hi> His mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was, that he should repent <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ause he could not tell whether he should live while to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrow; and that he should be <hi>always</hi> exercising repentance, that so whenever death should come, it might find him prepared for it; And to that purpose he makes use of the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> R. Solomon Jarchi in Eccl <hi>9 8</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Let thy Garments be always white, and let thy head lack no Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:33314:50"/>Eccl. 9.8. The Jews were commanded to <hi>afflict their souls</hi> at the day of <hi>Expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Maimonide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Levit. 16.29. And one of their Writers tells us, that they were then obliged to confess their sins, and to begin their confession the night before this day of Expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that before Supper also; and he gives this reason, <hi>because else perhaps he may be choaked in Supper-time before he hath made his Confessions.</hi> Alas, what do we mean to talk of repenting in our old age, when perhaps our breath may be stopt by the next morsel we eat, or our souls required of us this night; And it is the greatest folly in the world, to <hi>live</hi> in that state of things in which we shall be afraid to <hi>die.</hi> It was great folly in the Virgins, to have their Oyl to seek when the Bridegroom called. If we do not repent speedily, it is very probable we shall not repent
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33314:51"/>at all, and if we do not repent at all, we shall be unavoidably and eternally miserable: One delay may for ever hinder us; It is here as it was with the Pool of <hi>Bethesda,</hi> where we find he that first stepped in after the moving of the waters, was cured of his disease, <hi>John</hi> 5.4. He that repents presently may have pardon; but he that slips but one season, may perhaps never have it any more; for his life may soon be taken away, and then his hopes are ended. I have read a sad story of a Gentleman, who on his Death-bed imagn'd he saw certain Messengers that came to carry him away to Hel; wherupon he fell into great shrieks, and end his miserable life with these words,<note place="margin">Drexel. Trib. Christ, c. <hi>2.</hi> S. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Give me respite till tomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi> And <hi>Drexelius</hi> tells us a Story of another, of which he was wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness himself; Of a certain rich man that fell sick, and in his sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33314:51"/>was desired by some that stood by to lift up his minde towards Heaven: He fetched a great sigh, and told them, that he did look up towards Heaven, but that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the passage thither was now shut upon him. But what need I speak of these, how many have our own ears heard complain upon their uneasie death-beds, of the precious time they have lost, and the time they want, and cry out in vain, that their days might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed, <hi>O that men were wise, that they understood this, that they would consider their latter end,</hi> Deut. 32.39. O that we would be wise in time, for there is no wisdom in the Grave, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther we are making haste. We had need pray with the Psalmist, <hi>Teach us to number our days aright,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endred rightly. See <hi>Numb</hi> 27 7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6. And the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Pataph. on <hi>Ps</hi> 127.2. <hi>Ex.</hi> 10.29</note>
                  <hi>and we will bring a wise heart,</hi> Ps. 90.12. As
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33314:52"/>those words may be well translated, That is, Grant that we may not be mistaken in the right numbring of our days, in thinking them long<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r then indeed they are, and then this right numbring our days shall teach us Lessons of great wisdom. He is recorded for a <hi>Fool</hi> that promised himself <hi>many years.</hi> And certainly, he can deserve no better name that does so: we find many times, that the men that die <hi>suddenly,</hi> are those men that thought to have lived <hi>longest.</hi> Let us not say we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent <hi>hereafter,</hi> when we cannot tell but we may die <hi>presently.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But suppose thou dost live to old age, yet it is very <hi>uncertain,</hi> and <hi>a very great peradventure,</hi> whether thou shalt have the grace truly to repent or not. Nay, perhaps thou wilt die suddenly still, and never have the opportunity or the heart to call upon God for mercy. Thou mayst perhaps be given over, to an
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33314:52"/>hard heart, and a seared Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and tempted <hi>to curse God and die. The Lord,</hi> it may be, <hi>may be departed from thee, and become thine enemy.</hi> As it was with <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.15. It is most likely thou wilt die as thou didst live. What should make thee think, that the grace of God will follow thee to thy death-bed, and effectually bring thee home, after thou hast abused the love, and despised the grace of God all thy life time! Why shouldst thou think that God is so fond of thee, as that he will save thee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou wilt or not! Certainly we have more reason to fear, that God will no longer regard us, nor follow us with Intreaties, nor yet hear us though we cry loudly to him in our calamity: Let us well consider what the Holy Scriptures teach us in this matter, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.28.29.—<hi>Jer.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.18. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if in our youth and strength
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33314:53"/>we remember our Creator, as we are commanded, we shall be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For God hath not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to repent, and return to him, but to do it speedily, which if we do we may be assured of accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, for we have a Promise for it, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Esa.</hi> 55.6, 7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.17. But if we do neglect him <hi>Now,</hi> we have no assurance that God will regard us in our extremity. If we be profane, as <hi>Esau</hi> was, who sold his <hi>birth-right</hi> for a trifle, we have reason to fear that we shall lose our Fathers <hi>blessing</hi> also, and meet with the same event with him. <hi>For ye know that afterward, when he would have inherited the blessing, he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected: for he found no place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, though he sought it carefully with tears,</hi> Heb. 12.17. So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we should live to an old age, yet may we die in our impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and hardness of heart, in the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33314:53"/>love of our sins, and of this world: And thus we shall do if God leave us without his special grace, which we give him just cause to do. It is to be feared we shall die as we li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; the tree uses to fall that way that it is wont to lean towards. If we live without God in the world, it is much to be feared we shall die without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to him, and perhaps with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out so much as calling upon his Name, or crying to him for his Mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But suppose we do call upon God for mercy upon our Death-beds, and cry out upon our sins, yet we have great reason to fear lest we should play the Hypocrite at such a time as this. It is well if our Death-bed Repentance be any better then dissembling: We have great reason to suspect it is a <hi>forced, fained,</hi> and <hi>slavish</hi> thing.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33314:54"/>It is no wonder we cry out for <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> when we find Gods <hi>Justice</hi> too hot for us. We easily give our enemy fair words, when his dagger is at our breast, or his knife at our throat: When we are within the <hi>view</hi> of the <hi>flames</hi> of Hell, within the <hi>stanch</hi> of the <hi>Brimstone,</hi> and the noise of the <hi>miserable.</hi> When we see our selves just passing into an <hi>eternal destruction,</hi> no wonder that then we cry out for mercy. This may indeed affright us out of the <hi>action</hi> of <hi>sin,</hi> when yet we retain our <hi>affection</hi> to it. And though the sick man may cry out loudly for mercy at this time, and that with a bitter weeping, yet there are two conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations that will render this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance very suspicious; (1) If we consider how this Repentance commences, and is first wrought in us: It is to be feared, that it is only an effect of Gods <hi>Power,</hi> and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33314:54"/>
                  <hi>Vindicative Justice</hi> affrighting us, and not of his <hi>goodness</hi> that winns and draws us to him. We may cry out because we cannot <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand</hi> his <hi>power,</hi> when yet we do not grieve because we have <hi>abused</hi> his <hi>love.</hi> And such mens devotion is like that of the ancient Heathens to one of their Deities whom they worshipped <hi>ne noceret,</hi> lest their Deity should hurt them. Now most certain it is, that although the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God may <hi>scare</hi> us into some kind of Repentance, yet it is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the goodness of God that leads us to it,</hi> as the Apostle assures us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. The holiness and infinite goodness of Gods Nature, that he is infinitely better then all the World is, or can be, to us is the great inducement that brings a sinner home to God. Thus it was with the Prodigal son: <hi>When he came to himself he said, how many hired servants of my fathers have
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33314:55"/>bread enough, and to spare, and I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish with hunger; I will arise, and go to my father, &amp;c.</hi> Luke 15.17, 18. And thus it was with the people of <hi>Israel</hi> in the Prophet, who after they see the vanity of running from God, is brought home by this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement, <hi>Then shall she say, I will go and return to my first Husband, for then it was better with me then now,</hi> Hos. 2.7. For the Almighty Power of God is not of it self an inducement to a poor sinner to come to Him, for that rather speaks <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> then <hi>Encouragement.</hi> His pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may sooner make us be <hi>afraid</hi> of him, then <hi>fear</hi> him as we ought, or <hi>love</hi> him as we should. <hi>For he that cometh to God, must believe that He is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently seek him,</hi> Hebr. 11.6. There is <hi>Mercy</hi> with him, that he may be feared, <hi>We must fear the Lord and his Goodness,</hi> Hos. 3.5. Gods power may make us dissemble and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33314:55"/>fain our selves obedient at such a time as this: And that is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sure of those words of the Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist, <hi>Through the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of thy Power shall thine enemies submit themselvs to thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> LXXII. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Targ. <hi>They shall be found liar.</hi> See the old Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation. V. <hi>Ps</hi> 18.44. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.45.</note> Ps. 66.3. They shall submit themselves, that is, they shall yield a fein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed obedience, they shall dissemble or lie to thee, as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word imports. What we do at such a time, it is to be feared we are forced to; we cry out upon our sins because they have made us miserable, we would now part with them, because we know not how to keep them any longer with safety. We hate our sins because they are hurtful to us, and the rod of God is upon us.<note place="margin">Nemo invitus b<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne facit. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam si bonum sit quod facit. <hi>Aug;</hi>
                  </note> But if we might have our sins quietly, might we enjoy them in peace,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33314:56"/>we should not then hate them. Our Repentance is in great part against our will, and therefore cannot be true repentance: We do at such a time by our sins, as a Marriner in a tempest at Sea, does by his goods, who throws them into the Sea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but it is because his life is in danger in a sinking ship, and not because he is weary of his goods. And as this can hardly deserve the name of a <hi>free</hi> or <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary</hi> action,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> Aristot. Ethi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and a matter of <hi>choice,</hi> so may we very justly sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that repentance that begins up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no other accounts. For true Repentance is a free and voluntary Action. We must not think to impose upon God after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. He knows the voice of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> from that of <hi>Esau</hi> well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Verum nec nocte paratum</l>
                  <l>Plorabit, qui me velit in curvare que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relis.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33314:56"/>
               <p> The great and holy and all-wise God, will accept of nothing less then a true and unfeigned, and hearty Repentance; A forsaking our sins, and a free parting with them. But then again another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, that will make this death-bed Repentance very suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to be a piece of dissembling is this; That (2.) if we diligently observe the event of this matter, we shall many times find that those men that upon their sick-beds cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our so bitterly upon their sins, and so loudly for mercy, when God hath restored them to their health again, have embraced the very same sins which they lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before, and have bin as wicked, and far more wicked then ever they were before. Which as it is a clear evidence that this <hi>Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> was no better then plain <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie;</hi> so it may also teach us what little reason we have to trust
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33314:57"/>to such a Repentance as this, or to measure our selves by so uncertain and very fallacious a Rule. There are many men that in a sharp fit of sickness, or some great adversity, makes a very glorious appearance: You shall hear them complain of their forgetfulness of God, and tell you how they would live and serve God if he would spare them this once. But if you look upon these men after God hath restored them, you may find them many times far worse then ever they were known to be. Such men as these are like the topps that children play with, that will go no longer then while they are whipt: Thus the <hi>Israelites,</hi> when they were <hi>beaten,</hi> then they sought the <hi>Lord.</hi> But when <hi>Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run</hi> waxed <hi>fat,</hi> then he <hi>kicked. When he slew them, then they sought him, and they returned and enquired early after their God, and they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that God was their Rock, and the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33314:57"/>high God their Redeemer.</hi> Now a man would think this a very good people: But let us mark what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>Nevertheless they did flatter him with their mouth, and they lied un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him with their tongue. For their heart was not right with him, neither were they stedfast in his Covenant,</hi> Ps. 78.34.— For when God delivered them <hi>they soon forgot his works,</hi> Ps. 106.13. So far were they from being made b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tter by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which was Gods aim in laying them on, that they wearied God through their obstinacy, so that he complains of them by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Why should ye be smitten any more, ye will revolt more and more, <hi>Esa.</hi> 1.5.</p>
               <p>In a word, it was always so with that people, that however they sought the Lord in their <hi>Calamity,</hi> yet in their <hi>Prosperity</hi> they ran from him as fast: And the Lord tells them as much by the Prophet:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33314:58"/>
                  <hi>I spake unto thee in thy Prosperity, but thou saidst, I will not hear, this hath bin thy manner from thy youth, that thou obeyedst not my voice,</hi> Jer. 22.21.</p>
               <p>And therefore it was a wise say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Ben Sira, That we should ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour a Physician be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have need of him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Buxt. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ic. Rabbinic in NON.</note> That is, that we should honour God in our prosperity, if we would have him propitious to us in our adversity. To which we may adde what we reade in <hi>Siracides: Use Physick or ever thou he sick: Before judgement examine thy self, and in the day of Visitation thou shalt find mercy. Humble thy self before thou be sick, and in the time of sins shew repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Let nothing hinder thee to pay thy Vow in due time, and defer not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til death to be justified.</hi> Ecclus. 18. 19, 20, 21, 22. To turn to God in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33314:58"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n our youth and prosperity is a great Argument of the sincerity of our Repentance. Whereas we have great Reason to fear that our death-bed Repentance is but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of God, and that unto which we are <hi>craned</hi> and <hi>skrewed</hi> up by the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>errors</hi> of the Almighty, and not <hi>drawn</hi> to it by the <hi>cords</hi> of a <hi>Man,</hi> or the <hi>Bands</hi> of <hi>Love, Hos.</hi> 11.4. Whereas he that does truly repent and is converted, <hi>chooses</hi> to become a new man, and leads a new life, and would do so, if there were no <hi>Hell</hi> to <hi>punish,</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> to <hi>reward</hi> him. For he inwardly loves holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and hates sin with a perfect hatred. He is always acted by an inward vital principle that moves him and sets him forward. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the hypocrite is moved just like a <hi>Clock,</hi> or some such instrument, that goes indeed, but it is no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then there are certain weights hanging on, that they will move:
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33314:59"/>For they have no <hi>vital principle</hi> to actuate their wheels, and continue their motion: So is the <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> a kind of instrument that goes by <hi>Pulleys</hi> or <hi>weights,</hi> which may be taken away and laid aside, and then the motion is staid. Now the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite upon his sick-bed hath great <hi>weights</hi> upon him, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wonder that then he <hi>goes faster,</hi> but when they are removed, it is as little to be wondred at that he should <hi>stand still.</hi> This is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently expressed by <hi>Job,</hi> speaking of the Hypocrite, <hi>Will God hear his cry when trouble cometh upon him? will he delight himself in the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? will he always call upon God?</hi> Job 27.9, 10. In which words the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite is painted in his colours: <hi>He cries unto God,</hi> there's his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but it is when <hi>trouble</hi> comes upon him, that is the <hi>weight</hi> that moves him. For he wants an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward principle,</hi> for he does not <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:33314:59"/>in the <hi>Almighty,</hi> He wants a <hi>vital principle</hi> to continue his devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he will not <hi>always</hi> call upon God. The hypocrites Religion is a burden to him, it is not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant to his soul. He carries it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with him just as the Kine did the Ark to <hi>Beth-shemesh,</hi> who <hi>low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> as they went along, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.12. But the true servant of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to do his Will, and keep his Commandments, and <hi>His Commandments are not grievous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 1 John 5.3. That is, they are not heavy and burdensom to him. His Religion is become natural to him, and he is in great measure the same man in <hi>health,</hi> that he is in <hi>sickness:</hi> And when in a great trouble he vows obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God, he performs his vows, <hi>I will pay thee my vows which my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ips have uttered, and my mouth hath spoken when I was in trouble,</hi> Psal. 6. 13, 14. By what hath bin said it will
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33314:60"/>appear, that we have very great reason to suspect our death-bed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to be but hypocrisie, and so unavailable to our salvation. And this is another very great <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure</hi> and <hi>hazard</hi> that he runs that puts off his Repentance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Another great <hi>danger</hi> in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off our Repentance is this, that this is a step to final impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and unbelief, which is a si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that there is no pardon in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel for, a sin for which Christ ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver died, it being contrary to the whole design and purpose of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gospel. O consider, will it not h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a dreadful thing to die in thy sins and lie down in everlasting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings! How great will thy misery be, if thou <hi>die</hi> in thy <hi>sins,</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou might'st have been <hi>saved</hi> from <hi>them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quid illis miseriut, quihus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>se Salvator saluti non erit?</note> If thou ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eternally <hi>lost</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou hadst a <hi>Saviour</hi> that was read
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33314:60"/>to <hi>deliver</hi> thee! would it not be a disinal sight to see a friend or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dragged from his sick-bed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he flames of Hell. To hear him go howling down to the fire and brimstone! This will be thy sad portion if thou die in thy sins. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertainly when thou puttest thy Repentance off but till tomorrow, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou takest a step towards this sad Conclusion. For he that is now dead in his fins began with such single instances as now thou dost: when he was exhorted to repent he was wont to put God off, with a <hi>Not yet Lord,</hi> and, <hi>when I have a fit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eason, when I have passed my youth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd followed the designes of young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en.</hi> And then when God called, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e had married a wife, or hired a Farm, or is making a Purchase, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rafficking and getting gain, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aying up in store for the Winter of old age. And thus the man put God off, till death stopped his
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33314:61"/>breath, and spoiled his designes, and sent him away to his eternal misery: And then the poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is miserable, beyond all thought and all recovery. Thou sayst thou wilt repent tomorrow, and so perhaps thou wilt always say till all thy Sand be run out, and thy Sun be set, and there be no such thing as a <hi>Morrow</hi> left: when wilt thou make a stop if thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o not do it presently? Certainly, others have deluded themselves with these hopes, that are now among the <hi>dead</hi> and among the <hi>damned.</hi> They have said that they would repent ere long, but yet they left the world before they did this work, and are dead and miserable long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go. And how canst thou be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, when thou treadest in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry same path that hath led so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny down to the Chambers of Death? Canst thou expect the very same track should bring thee
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33314:61"/>to happiness, that brought thy Neighbor to his misery.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Another danger in delaying our Repentance is this, that so long as we remain without Repentance, God looks upon us as his enemies, and whatever we do is not accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his sight: we are in a state of nature and children of wrath, and all our prayers and confessions, &amp;c. are not accepted. <hi>The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 15.8. <hi>We know God heareth not sinners, but if any man be a Worshipper of God, and doth his Will, him he heareth,</hi> John 9.31. Till we have repented, God looks upon us as his enemies, for <hi>Warre</hi> is rather a <hi>State</hi> then an <hi>Action,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Grot de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Bell. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> and we are Gods enemies till we have laid aside our affection to our sin, and be reconciled to him. While we delay our Repentance, we stand out in our enmity to God, for a
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33314:62"/>
                  <hi>delay</hi> is no less then a <hi>denial.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Procrastinatio negandi instrumentum est. <hi>Card.</hi>
                  </note> He that puts God off, does as much as declare that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuses to be reconciled, and so does continue contumaciously an enemy to God. And God is also an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to him. And verily, did we know what it meant to be under Gods disfavour and displeasure, we would sooner choose the greatest miseries and torments in the world before it: If God withdraw our breath, we are lost for ever, and then we shall understand what Gods displeasure means, and shall find that there is <hi>no sorrow like this sorrow.</hi> And whiles we continue in this state, there is a very little distance between us and an eternal destruction. Methinks it should make an impenitent sinner startle, did he but consider how little a remove he is from eternal wrath, and that nothing keeps him from it
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33314:62"/>but a small thread of life, which as it may be easily snapt asunder, so when it is, he falls down to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable sorrows. Every man walks upon the borders, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Neighborhood of death; we read of one that said, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. e.<note place="margin">Vide Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. Laert. Anachars.</note>
                  <hi>The thickness of the Shipboard</hi> (which is not many inches) <hi>is the distance that the Mariner is in from death.</hi> And I am sure <hi>David</hi> said, <hi>there was but a step between him and death,</hi> 1 Sam. 20.3. And indeed every man may say it truly. The next <hi>step</hi> may be into his <hi>grave:</hi> But then the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent sinner is in a worse case; for as every man is upon the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>death,</hi> so is he upon the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>death,</hi> and of <hi>Hell</hi> too.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By every delay we harden our hearts against God, and the oftner we do this, the more unlikely will be our Return and Repentance. <hi>To
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:33314:63"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:33314:63"/>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:33314:64"/>day, if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts,</hi> Heb. 3.7. By delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to hear Gods voice we become more incorrigible, and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, and averse from every good word and work; till at length we get <hi>a Whores forehead, and refuse to be ashamed, and faces</hi> (and hearts too) <hi>harder then the rock that refuses to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> Jer. 3.3.5.3. And then in vain are all the <hi>Sermons</hi> that we <hi>hear,</hi> and the <hi>judgements</hi> that we <hi>see</hi> and <hi>feel.</hi> We are not <hi>shaken</hi> by the <hi>terrors</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> nor <hi>drawn</hi> by the <hi>Promises</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> nor <hi>allured</hi> by the <hi>voice</hi> of the wisest <hi>Charmer.</hi> We go on in our sins, and though God hedge in our way with thorns, yet is nothing able to turn us back. Thus it was with the Jewish peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Withhold thy foot from being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shod, and thy throat from thirst: But thou saidst, there is no hope: No, I have loved strangers, and after them I will go,</hi> Jer. 2.25. A dreadful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33314:64"/>we have of this in <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> God sent to him to dismiss his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; he works signs and wonders to convince him, but he hardens his heart. The River is turned into blood; he is plagued with frogs, with lice and flies; a Murrain falls upon his cattel, and boyls upon himself and servants: Thunder, Hail, Fire and Locust, and a thick darkness will not make him yield, till at last he dies miserably by the Hand of the Almighty; and he that would not <hi>obey</hi> Gods <hi>voice,</hi> must en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his <hi>hand.</hi> He that delays <hi>to day</hi> to hear <hi>Gods voice,</hi> does by God as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did, and the oftner he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats these <hi>delays,</hi> and reiterates his <hi>resistances</hi> to the Call of God, the less hopes is there of his return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="7">7. By our delays we provoke God to leave us, and to resolve to have no more to do with us, nor any longer to follow us with his
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33314:65"/>mercies. God may perhaps the next repulse swear in his wrath that his spirit shall never strive with thee more, and that thou shalt never enter into his rest; God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can tell how long he will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure our repulses, before he cast us off for ever. He can only tell how near we are to come to that fatal point from whence there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o retreating. 'Tis well observed that <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s heart was hardned, after the <hi>eighth resistance;</hi> whether God will beat so long with us we cannot tell: We have too much reason to fear, that the next resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance we make, may bring this dreadful stroke upon us. 'Tis to be feared we are advancing apace to <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s hardness of heart, unto which our acts of sin do set us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by way of <hi>natural causality,</hi> as well as by calling down the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Justice to compleat the sad change. Do we not perceive our
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33314:65"/>hearts grow more and more hard and inflexible; And that the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness which once we had wears away apace.<note place="margin">Res delicata s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Spiritus sanctus.</note> Be not too bold: The Holy Spirit of God is tender and may easily be grieved, and caused to depart from thee: His gentle fires may be quenched by thy obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy. <hi>Be instructed,</hi> O Jerusalem, <hi>lest my soul my depart from thee,</hi> Jer. 6.8. God deals with us, as with the Cities, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. He offers us terms of peace, but if we refuse to yield what can be expected, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an irreconcileable warre for ever. And then we shall be as without <hi>God,</hi> so without <hi>Hope</hi> in the world. And much better would it have been, that we had never heard of the <hi>mercies</hi> of the Gospel, which so unthankfully we have refused. If we put all these things together, we shall find that the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Repentance off to our
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33314:66"/>death-beds is very full of <hi>hazards</hi> and <hi>peradventares.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>I shall now proceed to shew the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great unreasonablenes of putting our Repentance off to our death-beds: I shall make it appear to be a very unjust thing, and very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable. And that I shall do in the following Severals.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. It is very unreasonable to serve God in the last place. To spend the greatest and best part of our time and strength in the slavery of the Devil and World, and to put God off with our dry bones. When we have a <hi>male</hi> in our flock, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up unto God a <hi>corrupt</hi> thing. Certainly, our Landlords and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters will not be served thus. It is a most unjust thing to offer up unto God, nothing but the ruines and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33314:66"/>spoils of sin, and the leavings of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil:<note place="margin">Non pudet te reliquias vitae tibi reservare. &amp; id foln in tempus benae menti destinare, quod in nulla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> rein conferri possit? <hi>Sen. ce brev. vit. c. 4.</hi>
                     </note> To present Him that, and that only, which we know not where else to bestow. We are not willing to serve <hi>God,</hi> till we can follow our <hi>sins</hi> no longer. We offer up unto God the <hi>wax,</hi> and keep the <hi>honey</hi> to other uses. We do as <hi>Saul</hi> did, who though he destroyed those things which were <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>refuse,</hi> sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them to the Divine Will, yet he spared <hi>Agag,</hi> and the <hi>best</hi> of the <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Oxen,</hi> 2 Sam. 15. And this is the greatest piece of unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness in the World. For if God be our Father and our Lord, our Master and our best Friend, to Him is due the best of what we are or have. Our youth and strength, the spring of our Age, and the principal of our strength
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33314:67"/>and time is only due to him.</item>
                  <item>2. It is very unreasonable to put off our greatest business to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, when we have least <hi>time,</hi> and least <hi>strength</hi> to do it in. Thus does he do that puts off his Repentance to his old Age and death-bed. This is as if two battels between the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite Armies, should begin to be fought at night, when they would presently be buried in darkness, and distracted with confusion. Our death-bed is not a fit place for so difficult and comprehensive a work. Repentance should be finished, and not begun, at such a time. The Jews were forbid to seek <hi>Manna</hi> upon their Sabbath-day, they were to gather enough upon the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that they might rest on that day of rest. The everlasting rest is approaching on our death-bed, we should not then be to seek when we are entring into our Rest. This would be just as if a man should
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33314:67"/>have all his days work to do when his time of sleep and rest is come: They were foolish Virgins, that when their Bridegroom called had their Oyl to seek, and in this very miserable time, that while they went to provide themselves with Oyl, <hi>the door was shut,</hi> Mat. 25. upon our death-bed our Lord calls us hence to receive the fruit of our ways, and therefore that is not a time to work. Besides, our death is sometimes very <hi>sudden,</hi> and then we have no <hi>time;</hi> And sometimes very <hi>violent,</hi> and then we have no <hi>strength.</hi> We are many times hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away to our graves, and there is no space or distance between our health and death. When it is thus we have no time for any thing, and therefore none for our Repentance. But yet suppose we lie a while up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our death-bed, yet then many times we are dead as to all the great purposes of life, and the ands of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:33314:68"/>Religion. Many times our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is laid asleep by a Lethargy or Apoplexie, or else mastered by the flames of a Feavor, or insolencies of a Phrensie: or at least much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scured by the steam of a black cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler: And when our Reason is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, it is too late to repent, and indeed impossible. But if nothing of this should happen, yet shall we find it task enough to conflict with our disease at that time: We shall have enough to do to support pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently under our present trouble. I have read of a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier under <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth,<note place="margin">Vide Strad. Bell. Belg. l. 1. Deca.</note> who beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging from the Emperour his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, a discharge from the Office he held under him, and the Emperour demanding of him the reason that moved him to lay aside his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, gave the Emperour this Answer, <hi>That between the day of</hi> death, <hi>and the Affairs of life, there
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33314:68"/>ought to interceed some space of time.</hi> A wise speech it was, and such an one as is thought to have had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon that Emperour, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire from his weighty Affairs, as History tells us he did. Sure I am it carries with it a great truth, for there is very much to be done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can die well, and it will be very unreasonable to put all that into so narrow a room as our death-bed is.</item>
                  <item>3. It is very unreasonable to put off our <hi>main</hi> business, and busie our selves about <hi>small</hi> and <hi>tristing</hi> things. And thus he does that puts his Repentance off till his death-bed. We account him a very weak man that goes to a Mart or Fair, to lay in necessary provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for himself and family, and yet spends his <hi>time</hi> there in <hi>hearing son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets,</hi> and his <hi>money</hi> upon <hi>gands</hi> and <hi>play-things.</hi> It is to be feared most men do thus: They live at that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33314:69"/>rate, as if God had sent them into the world to gaze, and to feed themselves fat, to rake together a little wealth, to wear gay cloaths, or be cried up for brave men. For these are the <hi>little</hi> things that we busie our selves about, and not to know God, and serve and love him, which yet is the great, and indeed only end for which God hath sent us into this world. It is a sad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration to think how long we live, and to how little purpose: History tells us of <hi>Julius Caesar,</hi> that when he read over <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> exploits, he wept, and told his friends, <hi>That whereas</hi> Alexander <hi>at his Age had overcome</hi> Darius,<note place="margin">Vide Plutarch. Apoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h.</note>
                     <hi>that yet he had done nothing of any remark.</hi> Well may we all weep, when we think that we have <hi>bin</hi> so long, and lived so <hi>little;</hi> that we have spent so <hi>many years,</hi> and done so <hi>little work:</hi> That at this Age we
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33314:69"/>have not mastered our passions, not subdued our desires, not weaned our selves from this vexatious World, nor become either fit to live, or fit to die. That we should spend so much time about our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and our pleasures, and be as far from God, and from Heaven, and farther too, then ever we were. <hi>We are careful, and troubled about many things,</hi> when we forget the <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num necessarium, the one needful thing, that good part that shall never be taken away from us,</hi> Luke 10.41.42.</item>
                  <item>4. It is very unreasonable to trust to our death-bed Repentance, and to say we will repent hereafter, because it will not be in our power to do it then, unless God follow us with his special grace, and enable us to do it. But whether he will do that or not we cannot tell, for besides that we give him just cause to abandon and forsake us; He
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33314:70"/>hath no where promised that, though we neglect him in our health, he will certainly remember us on our Death-beds, and then work a true repentance in our hearts.</item>
                  <item>5. It will appear very unreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, if we consider how we do in our worldly affairs: If we should transact our worldly affairs with no greater wisdom then we do the concerns and affairs of our souls, we should be taken for <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Madmen.</hi> In our worldly business we walk by certain <hi>saving rules,</hi> and <hi>prudential principles</hi> of good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry: We think it wisdom, <hi>to secure the main, to provide against Winter, not to let our Market slip, nor to refuse a good proffer and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to choose good seed and a good season for the tillage and sowing our Land.</hi> We account him a fool that <hi>withstands</hi> his <hi>Market,</hi> and <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects</hi> his <hi>Seed-time,</hi> and yet expects
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33314:70"/>a <hi>full purse,</hi> and a <hi>plentiful Harvest.</hi> We think him a mad man that sows <hi>tares,</hi> and yet confidently looks for a <hi>Crop</hi> of <hi>Wheat.</hi> We call him an ill husband that runs on <hi>score,</hi> and adds daily to his <hi>debts,</hi> but is neither careful to get them <hi>examined,</hi> nor get them <hi>crossed.</hi> We laught at a man that begins not to learn a <hi>trade</hi> till he be <hi>old,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins not his <hi>work</hi> till <hi>night,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Turpis &amp; ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la res est elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarius Sene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Ser. cp</hi> 36.</note> or that does not go to <hi>school</hi> till he is <hi>blind</hi> for <hi>old age:</hi> We should wonder to hear a very old man tell, that he is going to build himself a fair house, and that then he would travel into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ein parts, and then go into the Wars, and learn the modes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hions of the World. Should we see a man very dangerously wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his life bleeding out apace through his veins, that should tell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s he would seek for no help till
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33314:71"/>after so many days or months, how would such a thing astonish us. We should admire at the man, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drank a deadly poison una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, should speak of getting an Antidote the next Spring in order to his recovery. Who would not deride that man that should tell him that he expected as good wheat from the seed of cockle, as he might expect that sowed the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest wheat; and that it would be all one whether we sowed or not; or whether our seed were good or bad, so we did but trust the mercies of an Almighty God, who could send us a great Harvest without so much cost and pains; we should think him a vain man that should tell us, that he did not doubt, but in <hi>one day</hi> to do the <hi>work</hi> of a <hi>whole life:</hi> Or that, when he hath a very long journey to take, should affirm, that he had such a trust in the mercy of God, that he did not
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33314:71"/>question but to perform his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, though he sate still till the last moment; expecting no less from Gods Omnipotence, then what the Jews tell us hapned by a miracle to <hi>Jacob,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vide Targum J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. &amp; Microsol. in Gen. 28</note> when he went from <hi>Beer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheba</hi> to <hi>Haran;</hi> they tell us, that he went it in a day, and that the earth between <hi>Beersheba</hi> and <hi>Haran</hi> did leap to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him to meet him, and so sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him the labour of footing it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Such fools and mad men are we, we expect that Heaven should meet us, and save us the labour of any long pilg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>image: We look God should be so fond of us, as to be always working miracles for our sakes; and that when we will not be saved, that he should save us whether we will or not. We neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect our Seeds-time, and regard not what our seed be; we will not learn the way to Heaven, nor fight the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33314:72"/>good fight, nor run the race till old age come upon us: Our souls are wounded, and we neglect a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; we have a great journey to go, and much work to do, and yet we loiter or sit still; as if Heaven were nothing worth, and our souls of no value, or as if it were the most easie thing to get to Heaven, though our Saviour say, <hi>the gate is streight and the way narrow that leads to life, and that there be but few that find it,</hi> Mat 7.14. And certainly, we shall find it an harder matter to get to Heaven then we are aware of.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>I come now to take off those Objections that either might or have been brought against what I have hitherto said.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. The first I shall name, is
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33314:72"/>that which we reade at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Comon-Prayer-Book, before the late alterations made, cited from <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. And the words as they lie in that Book of Common-Prayer are these. <hi>At what time soever a sinner doth repent him of his sin from the bottom of his heart, I will put all his wickedness out of my remembrance, saith the Lord.</hi> From whence some are ready to inferre, that it will be all one whether we repent now or hereafter; nay far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that we are not obliged to an early Repentance, but may delay it to the last moment, because it is said <hi>At what time soever.</hi> And this is too commonly objected by men of <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>corrupt</hi> minds, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their delays. To which I answer,</p>
               <p>First, that though <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21, 22. be cited for these words in that Book of Common-Prayer, yet if we look the words in the Prophet,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33314:73"/>we shall find some difference. For the words in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> run thus: <hi>If the wicked shall turn from all his sens that he hath committed, and keep all my Statutes: and do that which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and right</hi> (note that well) <hi>he shall surely live, and not die.</hi> So that in this place there is no promise of Pardon to a wicked man, unless <hi>he turn from all his sins,</hi> and <hi>keep all Gods Statutes,</hi> and <hi>do that which is lawful and right.</hi> And certainly, this imports a great deal more then a crying out for mercy. He must <hi>forsake his way,</hi> and <hi>his thoughts too,</hi> Esa. 55.7. He must <hi>restore the Pledge,</hi> and <hi>give again what he hath robbed,</hi> and walk in the Statutes of <hi>life without committing iniquity,</hi> Ezek. 33.15. And therefore from these places can a man have no encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for his death-bed Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, for they loudly call for a good life and honest actions.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I answer, though God
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33314:73"/>have promised Pardon whensoever we repent, yet he hath no where made a promise that he will follow that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an with his grace,<note place="margin">Qui promis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti ventain, non promisit peccanti p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nitentiam.</note> which shall enable him to repent to his death-bed, who refuses and resists this offer of grace in the time of his health.</p>
               <p>Lastly, we must repent <hi>at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of our heart</hi> before we can have this Pardon; Now we know our hearts are deceitful, and we have great reason to suspect our death-bed Repentance to be feigned and hypocritical. It was a Speech of a very worthy man, that, <hi>he that will dissemble with God in his life-time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Greenh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>will dissemble with him in his death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. But some will say, God does as well accept, and as amply reward the old mans late Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as the early Repentance and Reformation of the young: He
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33314:74"/>gave as great a reward to those that went into his Vineyard at the eleventh houre, as he did to those that went in more early, and that did endure the heat and burden of the day: As may appear from that Parable which we read, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. And therefore there is no such need of an early Reformation, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet any such danger in a late on death bed Repentance. To which I shall answer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is by no means evident, that this Parable was ever meant in any such sense as is supposed in this Objection: For our Saviour hath no where told us, that by the <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth houre</hi> is meant <hi>old Age.</hi> No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have we, that I know of, the least shadow of reason to understand in in such a sense: But the design o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that Parable seems rather to be this, <hi>viz.</hi> to teach the Jews, who were Gods <hi>first</hi> people, that though God chose them <hi>first</hi> at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33314:74"/>of the world, yet would he now make his Name known to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, according as was foretold of old, and this he would now do in the days of the Messias,<note place="margin">The time of Christ, and of the Gospel, in which the Gentiles were to be called, may well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is elsewhere cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18. And is very often called, <hi>the end of the World, the last days or time,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eb: 1.2. Acts 2.17 1 Pet. 1.20. Heb. 9.26. Esa. 2.20.</note> in the end of the World, or <hi>the eleventh houre:</hi> and that though the Jews would repine at this mercy of God towards the Gentiles, yet notwithstanding their murmuring, (<hi>v.</hi> 11.) God would call in the Gentiles, and accept of and reward their services as largely as he would the Jews. As God rewarded <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Moses</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and all holy men among the Jews in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>everal times, so would he also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all good men, though Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, in these last times of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33314:75"/>And so an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writer expounds these words,<note place="margin">Theophylact. in loc.</note> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds the housholders going out early in the morning, to be meant of Gods calling his servants in the begining of the world to <hi>Noah,</hi> The Labourers of the third houre, to be those in <hi>Abraham's</hi> time; of the sixth, about the times of <hi>Moses;</hi> the ninth, the times of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets;</hi> the <hi>eleventh</hi> houre, the times of <hi>Christ.</hi> And verily, if we duly weigh this interpretation, (which is neither new, nor yet singular) and very well ponder on the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and following words, and all the parts of the Parable it self, with other very many passages of the Scriptures (which I must not now stand upon) and lay them well together, we shall find no consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Objection against it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, suppose that to be the meaning of the place, which is
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33314:75"/>pretended in this Objection, that by the <hi>eleventh houre</hi> is meant <hi>old age,</hi> and by the other <hi>houres</hi> is meant not the <hi>Age</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> but the several <hi>Ages</hi> of Mans life, yet it is very evident that this place is of no force in this business. For it is evident, that those men in the Parable, that went into the Vineyard at the <hi>eleventh houre,</hi> were not the same that were called or hired <hi>early in the morning, at the third, sixth, or ninth houre:</hi> For
<list>
                     <item>(1) Those that went in at the <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth</hi> houre were not called before, as they themselves tell the House-holder, when he <hi>asked them why they stood idle; They say unto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause no man hath hired us,</hi> v. 7. That is, this was the first offer that was made to them, nor do we read that ever they refused to enter in when they were invited: But now the case with us is quite different, we are called upon from day to day, in
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33314:76"/>our youth, in the early and first houres of our day, and we neglect and refuse, and delay our Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to our old age, and therefore cannot say with those in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>No man hath hired us.</hi> But again</item>
                     <item>(2) It is evident they were not the <hi>same</hi> men that went into the Vineyard at the <hi>eleventh houre,</hi> with those that were invited more early, because the Text tells us all along, and more particularly, <hi>v.</hi> 6. That the housholder at the <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth houre,</hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>found others standing idle;</hi> from whence it is evident they were not the same that were <hi>hired</hi> before: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for us, who are called at the <hi>third, sixth</hi> and <hi>ninth houre</hi> of the day, to put off our work to the <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh,</hi> is very unwarrantable. For it hath no warrantie from this place, nor is there one example in the Book of God to this purpose that may encourage us.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33314:76"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. But some will object the example of the Thief upon the Cross, who though he were all his life-time a very great sinner, yet did he find mercy from Christ at the last, even a little before his death: And therefore why may he not also have mercy upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who never committed those fins that that Thief might be thought guilty of.</p>
               <p>But I shall make it appear, that we can have no encouragement from this example of the Thief to delay our Repentance, and yet to look for a Pardon at last, when we lie a dying. Our case is far diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from his. For</p>
               <p>First, it does not appear, that this Thief ever heard of Christ before, we never read that ever he delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his repentance to this time, nor have we the least appearance of reason to ground any such opinion upon. And therefore his case is
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:33314:77"/>not the same with ours, and so it makes nothing for our purpose or excuse. For we have not only heard of Christ, but professed our selves his followers before we lie a dying, and yet we delayed a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repentance: Now what ground of hope can any man have from this example of the Thief, when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays his repentance to the last, when it does not appear that ever the Thief, after he heard of Christ, did delay his at all.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we have no reason to believe that our death-bed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance will be so sincere as this Thiefs was: Nay, we have too great reason to think it will not be so, for besides, that this Thief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Christ in his lowest condition, even then when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hung upon the Cross (which cannot be our case) and then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed an effectual faith in him: Besides all this he manifested as
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33314:77"/>true a Repentance and Faith, as that short space of time would give him leave. He acknowledged Christs innocence, his own guilt, and his trust in Christ for a future blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; further indeed he went not, nor could he after his first hearing of Christ, unless his life had been prolonged. But our case is farre different, for we after our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Christ despise and reject him. And therefore our Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is not like that Repentance of the Thief, unless it be in this, that it is <hi>late</hi> as well as his.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this is but one, and a very rare instance, the whole Book of God will not yield us such an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other example. This was a singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar instance of mercy which Christ never intended should be drawn into an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Privilegium per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonale ad alios extenditur.</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Inst. <hi>l.</hi> 1. Tit. 2.8.6.</note> or made into a Law; It was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal priviledge and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33314:78"/>grace, which is therefore to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no farther then the person. To conclude an universal and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral law from one fingular instance is very unreasonable: For any man to say, because this Thief was saved at the last breath, therefore he shall also, is extreamly weak and inconsequent.<note place="margin">Quod contra rationem juris re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epium est, non est producer dum ad consequentia. <hi>Vide Tir. digest. de Reg. Juris.</hi>
                  </note> For besides our case is so far different from that of this Thief, we may as well, nay, more reasonably conclude our certain <hi>misery</hi> from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the <hi>bad,</hi> as our <hi>happiness</hi> from the example of the <hi>good Thief.</hi> No man professing Christianity will have any ground to expect to fear as this Thief did.
<list>
                     <item>(1) Till Christ come into the world again, and</item>
                     <item>(2) Suffer again also, and that</item>
                     <item>(3.) Between two Thieves, and</item>
                     <item>(4) He be alive at that time, and</item>
                     <item>(5) Place where he suffers, and</item>
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:33314:78"/>
                     <item> (6) Be one of the Thieves; and</item>
                     <item>(7) The good one too: which thing I am sure will never come to pass.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. Some will say, God is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and can do what he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses: His Hands are not tied, he can save an old sinner as well as an old Saint: Nothing is impossible to him. To which I answer</p>
               <p>First, the question is not what God <hi>can</hi> do, but what he <hi>will,</hi> and what we have reason to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect he <hi>should.</hi> God can turn our <hi>stones</hi> into <hi>bread</hi> for us, and save us alive, though we cast our selves down from the highest rock or pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle. But yet we have no reason to expect these things when we are out of Gods way. As little reason have we to go on in our sins, and say, that God can save us notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, for the question being not what God can, but what he will do; the Scriptures must resolve us
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33314:79"/>in that; and sure I am, from the Scripture we have no reason to think he will. But</p>
               <p>Secondly, we have great reason to think he will not: what reason have we to think that God is so fond of us, that he will work <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> for us, when we despise the <hi>means!</hi> will he cause the <hi>Sun</hi> to <hi>stand still</hi> for us, because we have <hi>idled</hi> away our <hi>day!</hi> Or do we think God is so in love with us, as to save us, whether we will be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or not! Hath not God told us, that <hi>if we live after the flesh we shall die,</hi> Rom. 8.13. And do not the same Scriptures that tell us that God is <hi>Almighty,</hi> tell us also that he <hi>cannot lie,</hi> or <hi>deny himself.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. But some may say, is not God merciful as well as strong: Are not his compassions as great as his power! what pleasure then can he take in our death! Or why should we limit or restrain his
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33314:79"/>Mercies. To which I Answer</p>
               <p>First, that God is certainly ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry merciful, and delights not in our blood. We have sufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of his mercy every day. It is his mercy that hath still kept us within the <hi>hopes of Heaven,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>means</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> and on this <hi>side</hi> an <hi>eternal death:</hi> It is his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that he will accept of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and reward our sincere obedience; Had he desired our death he might have cut us off in the midst of our sins, and of our days, and given us a sad portion of all things among those that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally miserable. This mercy the very damned in Hell have had, in the time of their life, a great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of, and yet now are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally lost, because this abundance of Gods goodness did not lead them to Repentance, which is a most evident Argument, that the destruction of those that did abuse
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33314:80"/>and contemn the mercies of God, is no objection against Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. The sinner uses Gods mercie to evil purposes, and does by it as a shipwrack'd man does somtimes with a <hi>Planck,</hi> upon which he ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures so great a <hi>weight,</hi> as doth <hi>sink himself</hi> and <hi>it</hi> at once.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eroel. in Caim. Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag.</note> There are them that would have no God at all, that they might escape un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished; Others would have a God, but it is to right their cause. The <hi>Sinner</hi> would have a God that should be all <hi>mercy,</hi> that might <hi>wink</hi> at his <hi>follies;</hi> the Sufferer would have a God of <hi>Justice,</hi> who might <hi>avenge</hi> his <hi>injuries:</hi> And every one would have what he thinks for his own turn: I know no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why men should make such an Objection as this from the goodness of God, which they would lay hold
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:33314:80"/>of to excuse them from an early Repentance, whereas indeed the goodness of God leads them to it. But</p>
               <p>Secondly, God is just and holy as well as merciful! As the <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> of God forbears a while, so his <hi>Justice</hi> will punish us at last. It will be very <hi>just,</hi> that those should be <hi>condemned</hi> who <hi>will not be saved.</hi> That those should be destroyed who will not accept of Pardon. Do not tender fathers disinherit rebellious and wicked chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i immortales plurimum possunt, sed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n is plus velle nobis debent quam patentes; At pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, si pergimus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, suis bonis nos exheredant. <hi>Metel. apud A Gell. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> and bestow their substance on those that use it well! Certainly God will do no, less by us if we go on to rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him. The very same Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures which tell us of his mercies. tell us also of his Justice, and <hi>that he will by no means clear the guilty.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:33314:81"/>
               <p> I know not what farther Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction can be brought against what I have said, but still I am ready to believe, that what hath bin said will not be effectual to perswade the Reader to an <hi>early Piety,</hi> and a <hi>sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable repentance.</hi> Few men will be perswaded that their <hi>dying hour,</hi> and their <hi>day of Accounts</hi> are near at hand. It were well, if men could remember that death and judgment are then many times the nearest to us when we think them farther off. That servant that saith, <hi>his Lord delays his coming,</hi> shall find that <hi>his Lord shall come in a day when he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not for him, and in an houre that he is not aware of,</hi> Mat. 24.50. Luk. 13.35.17.26. We are <hi>secure</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often when we are not <hi>fafe.</hi> The old world little thought of a <hi>flood,</hi> when they gave themselves to eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and drinking, and giving in marriage; but the <hi>waters</hi> soon came down upon this <hi>ungodly</hi> world.
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:33314:81"/>The Sodomites little thought of a <hi>fire,</hi> and it rained <hi>fire and brimstone</hi> from heaven upon them: so shall it be when the Son of man comes: We shall deceive our selves till death undeceive us, and delude our selves with false hopes of a long life, till our Sand is all out, and time at an end. Certainly, many now in Hell little thought of <hi>dying</hi> so <hi>soon,</hi> much less of being <hi>there tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented</hi> after so short a life. The rich man in the Gospel little thought his soul should be taken from him <hi>that night,</hi> when he said to his soul, <hi>thou hast goods laid up for many years,</hi> Luk. 12.19. <hi>Belshazzar</hi> little thought surely of the <hi>expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> so suddenly, when he drank wine so securely in the vessels of the Temple, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. That which we least think of does often surprize and overtake us of a sudden: It is grown indeed for a Proverb, when
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:33314:82"/>we would express how little we think a thing, We say, <hi>We as little thought of such a thing, as we thought of our dying day.</hi> It seems we think but little of it, but yet it comes quickly upon us whether we think of it or no.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>Let me then exhort you in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Seck the Lord while he may be found,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Paraph. Kimchi &amp; R. Salom. in loc.</hi> — Sed sap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endum est &amp; qu dem maturè non enim nobis altera vita conceditur; ut com in hac sapientiam quaera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, in illa sapere possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, in hac u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> umque fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri necesse est, cito inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niri deber ut cito suscipi possit, nequid pereat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x vita cujus finis incertus est. <hi>Lactan. Inst l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note>
                  <hi>call ye upon him while he is near: let the wicked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake his way, &amp; the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons man his thoughts, and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will abundantly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Isa. 55.6, 7. That is, we must
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:33314:82"/>seek him presently, before the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree be past,</hi> or our <hi>life wasted</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed,</hi> as the Jews will expound that place. We must be wise betimes, and not project to be wise only at the last cast, though we live in folly in the mean time: We must both seek this spiritual wisdom, and use it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in this life. But with what words shall I perswade this? One would think, that what hath bin said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, should be sufficient, if it were duely considered, and without that nothing will be sufficient. Yet I shall add som considerations, which if we duly attend unto, may not be unfit for the purpose in hand.</p>
               <p>Consider then in the first place, and do it seriously, that your stay in his life <hi>cannot</hi> be <hi>long,</hi> but <hi>may</hi> be very <hi>short;</hi> and that after this uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain life is ended, the day of grace will be past with you, and you will have none of those termes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y offered which now you refuse.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:33314:83"/>The day is far spent with many of us, and the night is at hand in which no man shall work. Our time slides away apace, and with the very same pace do death and the grave, and the dreadful day of reckonings make their approaches to us. 'Twill be but a little time before our eyes shall be closed, and it shall be noised in the Neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that we are dead; When we have breathed a little longer, we shall breath our last. After a little longer stay, and traffick and jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, after a few nights and days, or, at most, a few Winters and Summers, we shall be call'd off this stage by death, and brought to judgement, and then our streets and houses in a short time shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that they know us; Then shall all our thoughts perish; and then if we have not <hi>repented</hi> in <hi>time,</hi> we shall to no purpose <hi>repent eternally.</hi> We shall be out of the reach of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33314:83"/>that mercy that now would gladly embrace us. We may then in vain call to the mountains and hills to cover us: we should therefore think upon how slender and weak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thread our eternal state does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end. We read of <hi>Absalom,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hung by the head upon an Oak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etween heaven and earth, and whereas one would have thought he might have cut off his hair, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o made his escape; one of the Jews <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ills us a tradition of the Rabbins, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat <hi>he drew his sword <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o cut off his hair,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">R. Salomon in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. 18.9.</note>
                  <hi>but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat he saw under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ath him Hell open,</hi> which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eady to receive him. How true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his Tradition is I examine not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut sure I am it well represents the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anger of the impenitent man, who is at all times, within an hairs breadth of everlasting burnings.</p>
               <p>Consider secondly, how gladly
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:33314:84"/>the damned in Hell would be of those offers of grace which we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and despise; Might they be taken out of their <hi>beds of fire,</hi> and placed again in the <hi>cooler regions</hi> of this world, and have such good terms of mercy p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omised them as we enjoy, how gladly would they embrace them? would they choose rather to lie in their <hi>flames,</hi> then to forsake their <hi>sins?</hi> Did we well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand what it is to lie <hi>down in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting burnings,</hi> certainly we should not so securely go on in our sins.</p>
               <p>Consider thirdly, what Answer can you make to God at the day of Judgment; if you continue in your impenitence, and neglect your own salvation; What will you say when God shall demand of you why you idled away your day; will you say, as those in the Parable, <hi>because no man hath hired us,</hi> Mat. 20.7. That we cannot, for God hath sent his
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:33314:84"/>Messengers that have told us both our <hi>work</hi> and <hi>mages,</hi> and beseeched us also to labour in Gods Vineyard. Will you say you had other things to minde first, your Merchandize, your Farms and Yokes of Oxen? That you cannot, for God had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to provide us with all these things if we would first seek the Kingdom of Heaven. Will you say you were not able? That you cannot plead, for God offers his Spirit to enable you for your ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. Will you say you did not think your time had been so <hi>short?</hi> But you had no as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance it should have bin so <hi>long:</hi> What shall we say then? God hath <hi>called</hi> us, but we would not <hi>hear him:</hi> He hath <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itten</hi> us, but we were not <hi>humbled;</hi> He shewed us <hi>mercy,</hi> but that would not <hi>soften</hi> us: He <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> but we were not <hi>afraid:</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:33314:85"/>He <hi>intreated</hi> us, but we were not <hi>perswaded:</hi> He sent his <hi>Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors,</hi> but they could not <hi>win</hi> us: He told us the <hi>danger,</hi> but we would <hi>venture;</hi> He propounded a great <hi>reward,</hi> but we <hi>neglected</hi> it; He mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> but we <hi>grieved</hi> his <hi>Spirit, despised</hi> his <hi>threatnings, believed not</hi> his <hi>Word:</hi> whom shall we blame now? Not our Maker certainly; For he gave his Son to die. Not our Saviour; for he did not cast us off. Not our Teachers; for they called upon us daily. Not our own weakness; for God was very ready to help us: Nor yet our want of time, for God was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to provide for us, and we had time enough to spare in sports and pastimes, in pleasure and in sin, in doing nothing, and that which was nothing to the purpose. It will appear, our destruction was from our selves, and that our mouths will be stopped when God calls us forth
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33314:85"/>at that great day of reckonings.</p>
               <p>Consider fourthly, how many and loud Calls you have to repent and return quickly: This is the voice of your heavenly Father, <hi>Turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways,</hi> Ezek 33.11. And this was the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Jesus Christ the Son of God, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15. And of the first Preachers of the Gospel, who call upon men every where to repent. This is the constant language of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times and very frequently in our <hi>awakened consciences,</hi> that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould repent quickly, every mercy of God calls upon us to Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce, for the Apostle tells us, that <hi>the goodness of God leads to Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce,</hi> Rom. 2.4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 3.9. Our health and strength, our plenty and our wealth call upon us to return, and <hi>ropent.</hi> And so do all the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and afflictions which we meet withal, they call upon us to <hi>repent</hi>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:33314:86"/>also; the blasting of our corn, the casting of our Calves, our unsea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Seeds-time, and our bad Harvest, the decay of our trade, and the loss of our Goods or good name, every sorrow and every sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness call upon us to <hi>repent quickly,</hi> and, to <hi>seek the Lord while he may be found:</hi> So the holy Scripture tells us, <hi>As many as I love I rebuke and chasten, be zealous therefore and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> Rev. 3.19. Nay, the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that befal <hi>other men</hi> also, they call upon us to <hi>repent.</hi> The <hi>Galile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> blood that <hi>Pilate</hi> shed, and the death of those by the Tower of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loam,</hi> these things preach to us that we must <hi>repent</hi> or <hi>perish,</hi> Luke 13.3, 5. The waters of the <hi>flood,</hi> the fire of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the destruction of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the flames of the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Temple,</hi> and all the other calamities of the poor <hi>Israelites</hi> call upon us to <hi>repent.</hi> The overthrow and ruine of Families, of Cities and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:33314:86"/>whether by Plague or Fire, Sword or Famine, call upon us to <hi>repent.</hi> In a word, every sad cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of our Neighbor, every asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing Providence that befalls him, preaches Repentance to us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud, and calls upon us to repent before the same, or greater plagues then these do overtake us.</p>
               <p>And that may be the meaning of what we read in the Psalmist, <hi>Thou turnest men to destruction;</hi> That is, thou inflictest great calamities upon men, <hi>and sayest,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> may, it is thought, be as well translated <hi>Repent</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Rotura,</hi> which lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r makes the sense mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>guous in this place.</note>
                  <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ye children of men,</hi> that is, thou givest men warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by these judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to <hi>Repent</hi> and <hi>Return</hi> from the evil of their ways. The many judgements of God in the world are so many loud warnings to the sinner to return and repent.</p>
               <p>Consider in the next place, that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33314:87"/>God is ready to receive thee, and to embrace thee upon thy Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, how many or great soever thy sins have been: He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents shall be welcom unto God: That God, whom we serve, does not delight in our death, but is greatly pleased that we should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and live.<note place="margin">Heus tu peccator bon o animosis, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos ubi de tuo gaudeatur. <hi>Tert, de poenitent.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>There shall be joy in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over one sinner that repents,</hi> Luk. 15. So our blessed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath told us more then once in that most comfortable Chapter, where we shall find this truth vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously exemplified to us. When the Prodigal son was coming home, <hi>When he was a great way off his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saw him, and had compassion, and ran and fell on his neck and kissed him:</hi> And he makes merry for his son when he comes home, as we may read in that Chapter: Come then, poor sinner, come whiles
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:33314:87"/>God calls thee, and he will bid thee welcom: Come thou great sinner, that hast heaped one sin upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thou old sinner that hast li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved many years in sin: Come thou burdened and weary finner, Christ <hi>will give thee rest:</hi> He will in <hi>no wise cast thee out:</hi> Mat. 11.28. John 6.37. Thou wilt make joy in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a great joy among the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God, nay, God himself waits for it, and will be greatly pleased at thy <hi>Return.</hi> Thy sins, how great or many soever, shall be blotted out, thy Name shall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled in the Book of life, among the Friends of God and Citizens of Heaven, and thou shalt at length sit down with <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Isaac,</hi> and all the holy men and Angels of God to eternal Ages. Come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way then, O sinner, stay no longer among the Swine, feed no longer on the husks, the Garlick and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyons, leave off thy sius, and foolish
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:33314:88"/>pleasures, and turn unto thy God; He is ready to meet thee, and thy Saviour to embrace thee: God hath sent his Ministers to tell you, that the Supper is ready, and he hath sent us out to call in the <hi>poor and maimed,</hi> the <hi>halt and blind,</hi> that is, he hath given us commission to call in the vilest and unworthiest sinners, and to assure them that they shall be welcom, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.16. And therefore in the Name of God I call you, and I do it again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Turn unto the Lord, O sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and thou shalt live and not die; God never sent away a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting sinner without mercy: <hi>Draw nigh unto God, and he will draw nigh unto you,</hi> Jam. 4.8. The devil will be apt to perswade thee that God will not accept thee, that he will not pardon, and that he hath no mercy for such an one as thou art; when he cannot ruine thee by <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity,</hi> he will endeavour to do it by
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33314:88"/>
                  <hi>despair:</hi> But believe him not, for God will receive thee unto mercy, if thou do unfainedly turn to him. Hear rather what God says him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self: <hi>As I live, saith the Lord God, I have no pleasure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live: turn ye, turn ye, from your evil wayes, for why will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o die, O House of Israel,</hi> Ezek. 33.11. Where God doth not only <hi>say</hi> it,<note place="margin">O nos usiser <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos si nec jur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ii Domino cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus. <hi>Tert. de Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>irent.</hi>
                  </note> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it with an <hi>Oath</hi> also, <hi>that we might have a strong consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope set before us,</hi> Heb. 6.18. How wretched are we if we do not believe God when he swears by himself, and the thing it self is so very evident and plain! If God had desired our death, he might have destroyed us long ago, what could have hindred the Almighty: He might have sent the Sinner to Hell
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33314:89"/>from the last <hi>drunken meeting:</hi> The last time he let Oaths flie out of his mouth, he might have present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly stop'd his mouth with <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimstone,</hi> and thrown him into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting burnings: The mercy of God hath kept him from being consumed: And all the patience and forbearance of God hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly testified that he <hi>stayed</hi> for his <hi>Conversion,</hi> but <hi>delighted</hi> not in his death.</p>
               <p>Consider in the next place this also, that if you neglect to repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now, and to secure your souls, that this exhortation will bear witness against you at that great day. And how sad will it be, that that which was intended for your <hi>Conversion,</hi> and <hi>eternal welfare,</hi> should turn to your <hi>Confusion.</hi> This will be worth our serious reflection. When we lie a dying, or when we appear before our Judge, and our Consciences are throughly awakened, this reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:33314:89"/>on will appale our hearts, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully perplex us. When we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that in our health we were told of these things, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated earnestly to <hi>seek the Lord while he might be found,</hi> and when we consider how securely we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected this exhortation, and put God off from time to time, till at last time was no more, how will such thoughts as these amaze and confound us. Go now to a man that lies a dying, who hath thus dealt with God, and if he be awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before he dies, he will tell you a sad story: <hi>Alass (will he say) wretched man that I am, who shall now help me? I have been often told of death and judgement, and of the wrath of God against all unrighteousness, and frequently called upon to repent, and seek the face of God betimes: But I have put these thoughts far from me; I have followed my lusts, my sports and worldly business, and made my heart so
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:33314:90"/>hard, that the mercies of God, nor the terrors of the Almighty could overcome it, and now I see nothing before me, but the bottomless pit, and an unspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able sorrow; O that I could now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the houres which I have spent in doing nothing, or in doing wickedly: O that I had that time which I spent in Taverns and Plays, in dressing and courting, in foolish divertisements and impertinent visits, after the honours, and pleasures, and profits of the world; how could I now spend them in the house of Prayer, and the exercises of Religion?</hi> Thus do many wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed creatures bewail themselves upon their uneasie beds; Some indeed, that never make such com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints there are, although they have lived very wickedly, yet these mens eyes are opened when they approach their Judge; and are awakened with the flames of Hell about them. Now certainly, as we would not be thus extreamly
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:33314:90"/>miserable, it will concern us to think of these things before they come to pass; And would it would please the Almighty so effectually to put these thoughts in our hearts <hi>now;</hi> that <hi>hereafter</hi> we might not be confounded and overwhelmed with them.</p>
               <p>Consider lastly, what I said and proved before, that you must <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> or <hi>perish, That unless you be born again you can never enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> You will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver see God <hi>hereafter</hi> without an <hi>inherent</hi> and <hi>universal holiness here;</hi> Should I teach you any other do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I should be a most notorious <hi>deceiver,</hi> and a false <hi>Prophet.</hi> Nay, should an Angel from Heaven preach any other doctrine, we ought not to believe him. This it the <hi>peculier eminence</hi> of Christian Religion, as well as the undeniable Argument of the truth of it, that it does indispensibly require an
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:33314:91"/>holy life in order to a future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness; And whatever doctrine or Religion doth dispense with this, we may safely conclude it never came from God; It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that the lives of most men, and the doctrines of very many, would seem to insinuate that this is <hi>not true;</hi> But sure I am, the <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>doctrine</hi> of our blessed Saviour teach us no less. And if we make that our rule, we shall be eternally deceived and undone, if we do not become <hi>new creatures.</hi> Nothing less then this will serve your turn at the <hi>long run;</hi> And therefore choose whether you will <hi>repent</hi> or <hi>perish;</hi> part with thy <hi>sins,</hi> or with thy <hi>God,</hi> thy <hi>soul,</hi> thy <hi>hopes</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and whatever ought to be most dear unto thee: The <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> is a streight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure, which hath no <hi>Posterns</hi> to let in false people at. Here is no <hi>indulgence</hi> or <hi>dispensation</hi> to be had
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:33314:91"/>which might give a certain <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedeas</hi> from the labours and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities of an holy life. All that pass into Heaven must go through that <hi>narrow gate</hi> which leads into it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>And now I might have done, one would think, and conceive good hopes that you would no longer halt between two opinions, but that every man should strike his own breast, and sadly think what he hath done, and set upon an effectual and speedy Reformation. To the doing of which we have very great Arguments to move and perswade us, as appears by what hath bin said above. But yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we are easily obstructed and kept from so holy and good a work, I shall, before I make an end, shew what are those usual <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances</hi>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:33314:92"/>that <hi>keep,</hi> and so greatly entangle them that they do not proceed o a sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edy and effectual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and amendment of life.</p>
               <p>The first <hi>Hindrance</hi> I shall name, is this; Men say they are <hi>not able</hi> to <hi>repent</hi> and <hi>amend</hi> of themselves, and therefore in vain do we exhort them to it. They can do nothing, they say, which is good: There is a <hi>spiritual Cramp</hi> upon them, by which they are disenabled to move towards any thing of amendment of life. This doctrine they have bin taught, and they are willing to believe it most true. I shall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore examine the truth of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. And</p>
               <p n="1">1. I observe the forwardness and folly of these men who plead this excuse, when they are exhorted to repent, they say they <hi>cannot,</hi> but yet at other times they put off their repentance to the houre of death, and in so doing they suppose they
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:33314:92"/>
                  <hi>can repent</hi> when they will: when they <hi>sin,</hi> they say it is but <hi>repenting,</hi> and all will be well; but when they are called upon to do that <hi>specdily</hi> and <hi>effectually,</hi> then they pretend it is <hi>impossible.</hi> Sometime they suppose it a <hi>very easie thing,</hi> and another while altogether <hi>above their power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is very plain, that the great fault lies in our <hi>will,</hi> and not in the <hi>want of power,</hi> however we may deceive our selves. This will be made appear at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to every one of our faces; Nay, this may easily be made evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent now also. For
<list>
                     <item>(1) That God commands things <hi>absolutely impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible,</hi> is a doctrine very false, of whomsoever we have learned it,<note place="margin">Execramur corum blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemiam qui dicunt impossibile aliquid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini à Deo praecepium esse, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hier, <hi>epist. ad Damasom.</hi>
                        </note> and hath of old been thought a pernicious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. For who
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:33314:93"/>sees not, if this were true, that the Gospel would then be of no use at all, if it did only oblige us, and not help us; if it commanded things impossible to be done, and should there leave us to an inevitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction; But the fault lies in our will: for</item>
                     <item>(2) If we were willing and resolved, we should not sit still and say we could not amend, but we would try our utmost whether we could or not: At least we</item>
                     <item>(3) Should carefully use those means which God hath appointed for our salvation. Though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not work grace in our hearts, yet we can hear Gods Word, and read it, and be frequent in the house of prayer: The sick man cannot la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in his Fields, but yet he can take Physick, use a good diet, and follow the rules of his Physician, and by that means may become strong to labour again.</item>
                     <item>(4) How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we should not be so well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:33314:93"/>in this condition, if there were not a fault in <hi>will.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Though we <hi>cannot</hi> alone, yet with <hi>Gods help</hi> we may amend our hearts and ways: We say, <hi>a man can do that which he can do by the help of his friends:</hi> God is as willing to help us as a <hi>tender father</hi> to help a <hi>child,</hi> carry that burden which he sees too heavy for him. It is a most true saying, that <hi>He that sets himself upon amendment of life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Qui se ad mandationem accingit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juvatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <hi>will find help from Heaven.</hi> This is a very certain truth, that a Christians power and assistance is at least equal to his work: God is not so hard a Master as to command us things absolutely impossible: I shall therefore prove, that if men will make use of that power which God hath provided, they will have no reason to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain. For it will appear, that God hath commanded nothing, but what
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:33314:94"/>he is very ready to help us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; so that if hereafter we miss of Heaven, we shall have reason only to blame our selves. For if Gods <hi>commands</hi> are <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult,</hi> yet his <hi>assistances</hi> and <hi>helps,</hi> if made use of, are very <hi>great</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable.</hi> The Gospel does not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>command,</hi> but it <hi>enables</hi> us to <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,</hi> It does not only <hi>require obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> but it also <hi>gives grace.</hi> It doth indeed <hi>expect much from us,</hi> but then it doth <hi>bestow as much.</hi> I shall therefore name those helps and powers which God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided us withal.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) He hath promised the <hi>assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and this must needs be a very great and effectual assistance. And God hath assured us that he will bestow his Spirit on them that ask him, as readily as a father will give bread to his child that begs it of him: Nay, more readily, for if earthly Parents will
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:33314:94"/>give good gifts unto their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>How much more shall our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father give the holy Spirit to them that ask him?</hi> Luke 11.13. No promise can be more plain, none can be more comfortable then this is. And if therefore we do but <hi>humbly</hi> and <hi>heartily</hi> beg this holy Spirit, as an hungry child cries for bread, if we do not <hi>quench his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> nor <hi>grieve his Presence,</hi> we shall not only obtain him, but we shall find his assistance very effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual. We shall have no cause to complain that we are weak and feeble, no reason to fear that our sins should be too hard for us; But we shall find, <hi>that he that is in us, is greater then he that is in the world,</hi> 1 John 4.4. That is, we shall find the holy Spirit which is in us, not only enabling us to support, but to vanquish and overcome the Devil and all his Powers; Fear not them, but remember who is on thy side,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:33314:95"/>and that God provides for thy security. Be not dismayed at the devil and all his host, the Spirit of the Almighty, that Holy Spirit of power is engaged on thy side, I will speak to you in the words of the Prophet <hi>Isaiah, Fear not, O Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, my Servant, and thou</hi> Jeshurun <hi>whom I have chosen: For I will pour water upon him that is thirsty, and floods upon the dry ground; I will pour my spirit upon thy seed, and my bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing upon thy off-spring,</hi> Isa. 44.2, 3. A Christian hath greater strength then he is aware of, a greater power engaged <hi>for him</hi> then <hi>against him.</hi> Indeed he is apt to be afraid and to despond, but that is because he does not know his own strength. The Prophets servant was more afraid then he needed, when his Master was besieged, but the good Prophet bids him not fear, <hi>For they that be with us,</hi> says he, <hi>are more then they that be with them,</hi> 2 King. 6.16. And
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33314:95"/>his servant saw it too when his eyes were opened. It is just so with the weak Christian; the devil perswades him he hath great Armies and Hosts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainst him, but if his eyes were open, he would see his <hi>strength</hi> greater then his <hi>enemies.</hi> If God be with us, who can be against us? Now the holy Spirit of God will help us <hi>mightily,</hi> if we humbly beg his aid, and cherish his motions, and sincerely follow his guidance and his conduct.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another help, and very great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncouragement which the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an hath, is the consideration of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife and death of our Lord Jesus Christ. That great example which he hath left us will be of very great moment to our amendment, if we do but duly reflect upon it. The sight of this brazen Serpent one would think, should cure our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers, and heal the corruption of our natures. The great example of
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:33314:96"/>our Lord, were it always before our eyes, how would it animate and encourage us in our Christian course! Methinks we should ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture on that path which our Lord hath walked in before us: we should not be afraid of those diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties which our Lord hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: nor dismaid at those trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and enemies, which the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of our salvation, did most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedly despise and conquer. It is a great encouragement to the <hi>common souldier</hi> to see his General engage himself in the greatest dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and to triumph over them; such an example shews him at once what he <hi>may</hi> do, and what he <hi>ought.</hi> And verily, the example of our blessed Saviour should have the same influenee upon us: How can we be <hi>proud,</hi> when he was <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>lowly</hi> in heart! Why should we <hi>complain,</hi> when he was <hi>patient</hi> even unto death! we may well <hi>forgive
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:33314:96"/>an enemy,</hi> when our Saviour prays, <hi>Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do;</hi> and well may we be <hi>contented</hi> with our condition when we remember the words of our Saviour, when he was about to drink the most bitter cup, <hi>Not my Will, but thy Will be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Another help the Christian hath is, the intercession of our Lord Jesus Christ in Heaven for him: Did he rightly consider Jesus Christ at the right hand of his Father, he would not certainly be thus feeble hearted. This consideration would adde a mighty vigour, new strength and courage to every drooping Christian, and to every young Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert. Though our Saviour died upon the Cross, yet he revived again, and is yet alive, and appears before God in our behalf: <hi>He is able to save them unto the uttermost that come unto God by him, seeing he ever liveth to make intercession for them.</hi>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:33314:97"/>Hear this for thy great comfort thou hast an High Priest in Heaven one that can pity and compassionate thee, and one that will help and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour thee: One that knows thy wants, and pities thine infirmities: <hi>We have not an High Priest that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be touched with the feeling of our infirmities: but was in all Points tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like as we are.</hi> And <hi>in that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self suffered, being tempted, he is able to succour them that are tempted,</hi> Heb. 14.15.2.18. These words bring with them a very great consolation to the drooping sinner: He is not lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alone, and forsaken, God is with him: His blessed Saviour hath been tempted himself, and even now is very mindful of those that are tempted.</p>
               <p>The next <hi>Hindrance</hi> I shall name is this, which some men may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to stumble at. They judge thus, if God have elected and chosen them, his Decree shall stand, and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:33314:97"/>they shall certainly be saved at last; But, <hi>say they,</hi> if God hath passed us by, then all our endeavours will be to no purpose. And therefore we shall not need be sollicitous about such matters as are already <hi>fixed</hi> and <hi>determined</hi> by the <hi>unalt rable</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of God, and who hath resisted his will?</p>
               <p>And thus does the devil mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably cheat and delude the poor sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by his strange reaches and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices. Now I shall say something to this pretence in these following Severals.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. It is certain that Gods decree is not the rule of our life, but his written Word and declared Will. If we open our Bible we shall finde that, <hi>He that believes shall be saved.</hi> This is the language of the Holy Scriptures: 'Tis a great place of pride and folly in us, to be gazing on high for our direction, when our way lies so plainly before us. We
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:33314:98"/>need not climb into Heaven to make a search or no, whether or no we are enrolled in the Book of life <hi>The World is nigh thee: if thou shall confess with thy mouth the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, and shalt believe in thine heart, that God hath raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved,</hi> Rom. 10.7, 8, 9. If we repent and believe the Gospel, it will go well with us at the last and great day; but if we live and die in our sins, we shall be unavoidably miserable; if we obey the Gospel, no decree of God will shut us out of Heaven. And if we continue in our sin and unbelief, no decree of his will bring us thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                  <item>2. It is agreed on all hands, that there is no decree of God shuts up a man under a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of sinning and being damned.<note place="margin">Bishop <hi>Davenant</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Hoord,</hi> c. 2.</note> Sin does not follow from Gods pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a man, as an effect slows from
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:33314:98"/>its proper and true cause, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a mans damnation cannot flow from it.</item>
                  <item>3. And therefore at the day of judgement, the sentence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation will not lay hold upon men, because <hi>they were not elected,</hi> but because <hi>they were wicked, and did not obey the Gospel.</hi> It shall be said to the wicked at that day, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me ye cursed into everlasting fire, &amp;c.</hi> And wherefore is it? Not because they were inevitably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to it, but for their own wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dness, as it follows, <hi>For I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meat; I was thirsty, and ye gave me no drink, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. If Gods decree were to be our rule, no man could have any ground at all for his faith, and the Gospel would be a most useless and ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual thing, which would be most absurd to believe. For we know that there is in the Gospel the
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33314:99"/>greatest ground for every mans <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> that is imaginable: We have great encouragement to receive the mercy which God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers us by his son: If we do not shut our selves out, our Saviour doth not exclude us. The Gospel opens a large door of hope, if we do not shut it upon our selves. <hi>Him that cometh to me,</hi> says our Saviour, <hi>I will in no wise cast out,</hi> John 6.37. Did our Saviour put any back, because they were <hi>not elected,</hi> and therefore he could not receive them? Did he require any more then this, that they should <hi>repent</hi> and <hi>obey th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Gospel?</hi> If he be so <hi>merciful</hi> as not to shut us out, why should we be so <hi>cruel</hi> as to exclude our s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lves? Did the Apostles and first Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Gospel, require any mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of their Converts but fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? Was not this all that <hi>Philip</hi> required of the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> of the Goaler,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:33314:99"/>that they should believe in the Lord Jesus? <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36, 37.16.30, 31. No man that beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ves shall miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and there is in the Gospel all possible encouragement for our faith.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And therefore ought we not to make the way to Heaven more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row then it is, and to ruine our selves by our groundless fears, when our <hi>duty</hi> is so <hi>plain,</hi> and our <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> so <hi>great.</hi> It will well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come us to work whiles it is day, before we are buried in an eternal darkness. If we sit still whiles our time spends, and our day makes haste from us; if we dispute over our work, and neglect to do it, we shall soon sit down in everlasting sorrows. 'Tis a sign we neither love our work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or yet our Master, when we are so easily discouraged from it. Sure I am, that he which values his life, will take care how to preserve it, though he should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:33314:100"/>the term of it <hi>fixed</hi> and not <hi>moveable:</hi> For certain it is, that he will die if he fit still and do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think, and so shall we also if we be not wise betimes.</p>
               <p>Another <hi>Hindrance</hi> is this. Men are not willing to repent as yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they look upon Religion as a very <hi>hard saying,</hi> a <hi>Melancholick</hi> and very <hi>grievous discipline:</hi> And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may become sage, and aged persons, it is not thought fit for the active and the young, who must not look to see a good day ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This generally is the pretence of young persons against a religious life: I shall desire these men to consider impartially these following things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether it be not a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just thing that those men should pass this censure upon Religion, that never made any trial of it. 'Tis very unequal that the same man should be both <hi>Accaser</hi> and <hi>Judge;</hi>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:33314:100"/>And that a man should <hi>condemn</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath <hi>convicted;</hi> Now this is the pretence of the profane and irreligious, who have no reason to <hi>pronounce</hi> against Religion, which they have had <hi>no experience of. A blinde man is an incompetent Judge of colours,</hi> but yet not more incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent then these men in the matters of Religion; Christ himself will not escape a <hi>severe sentence,</hi> if <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate</hi> may be allowed to be the <hi>Judge,</hi> and his <hi>enemies</hi> his <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us consider which is the harder saying of these two, <hi>Repent,</hi> or <hi>Perish: Repent,</hi> or <hi>lie down in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting burnings.</hi> Which is the <hi>harder saying</hi> of these two, <hi>Repent and believe the Gospel,</hi> Mark 1.15. Or, <hi>depart ye cursed into everlasting fire,</hi> Mat. 25.1. Certainly, the sinner that shall fall into the hands of Gods Justice, will find no sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row like that sorrow: And though
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:33314:101"/>he may now think <hi>Repent</hi> an hard saying, yet he will find <hi>Depart ye cursed</hi> very much harder. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thought <hi>Solomon</hi>'s an heavy yoke, but that was light to that which they must expect from his Son, whose little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inger would be bigger then his fathers loins. We must bear the <hi>yoke of Christ,</hi> or, the <hi>chains of darkness:</hi> we must <hi>return</hi> unto God by a new life, or else <hi>be turned into Hell with all the Nations that forget God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The injunctions of Sin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan <hi>are hard sayings</hi> also, nay, <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rder</hi> then the exercise of Religion, and therefore the sinner hath no reason to use this pretence. Men serve an hard Master when they serve the devil or their own lust; and yet this they do without complaining, though they command them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable and contradictious things, and in stead of rewarding them for their pains, deprive them
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:33314:101"/>of their innocence, their peace and comfort, the favour of God, and the hopes of Heaven. And yet we complain that God is an hard Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, though he both <hi>reward</hi> us, and <hi>help</hi> us to <hi>do</hi> our work. Did we serve God as industriously as we serve the devil and the world, we might be happy with the same pains that now we are miserable. It is no small pains the sinner many tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s is at to be undone. He digs his grave, aye, and makes his way to hell with no small difficulty, We can take any <hi>pains</hi> to be <hi>miserable,</hi> but will take none to be <hi>happy.</hi> If the thing were rightly considered, there is more of <hi>pain</hi> in a dissolute life, then in a Religious; in the <hi>works</hi> of the <hi>flesh,</hi> then in the <hi>fruits</hi> of <hi>righteousness,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Theophyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. in Gal. 5.12.</note> and of the <hi>Spirit.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle reckons up good and evil
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:33314:102"/>works, the good he calls the <hi>fruits</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is very kindly expressed; but the evil he calls the <hi>works</hi> of the <hi>flesh;</hi> as it is thought, to let us know the <hi>difficulties and labours of a sinful course,</hi> Gal. 5.19. —22.— And certainly, if we would be at the pains to consider it, we should find that those <hi>fruits</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> are much more easie and joyous then the works of the <hi>flesh.</hi> Let us but compare them a little, and we shall find it true. <hi>The fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, long-suffering, gentleness, goodness, faith, meekness, temperance.</hi> What is there here that will put us to any pain or sorrow: Nay, then afford us much quiet, and are attended with an ease that the works of the flesh will not admit of: Now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the works of the flesh he reckons <hi>Adultery, Hatred, Variance, Strife, Seditions, Envyings, Murders, Drunkenness,</hi> and <hi>Revellings.</hi> Now
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:33314:102"/>what sorrows do not these things bring upon us? who can express the <hi>sorrows</hi> and <hi>pain</hi> of <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Drunkenness!</hi> the <hi>torments</hi> of <hi>Envy!</hi> the <hi>turmoils</hi> and <hi>confusions</hi> that come from <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Seditions!</hi> the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>easiness</hi> of <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Variance!</hi> and the very <hi>Hell</hi> which he lets into his soul, who is guilty of <hi>Revellings</hi> and <hi>Murders!</hi> will any man believe that <hi>Drunkenness</hi> is easier then <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance;</hi> Or that <hi>love</hi> hath as much of pain as <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Envy;</hi> or that the <hi>chaste</hi> meet with as many sorrows as the <hi>Adulterer</hi> doth; may not any one perceive, that <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>gentleness</hi> and <hi>meekness,</hi> are much more pleasant then <hi>Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and <hi>Revellings, Seditions</hi> and <hi>Murders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the sinner hath no reason to use this pretence against Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for 'tis but a cheat and delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion:
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:33314:103"/>'tis a false report brought up by a wicked Spie. The devil does by Christian Religion as the old Heathens did by Christians. They put them into the skins of wilde beasts, and then they worried them. He misrepresents a most excellent Religion, and then his instruments assault it. But certainly, the sinner in the maan time will be left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuse, he is afraid of that which would not hurt him: And those that have been industrious in the service of God can tell him, that they can find no fault with their Master or their work.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let him that thinks Religion so great a slavery, look at the end of it. 'Tis great wisdom to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the end of a matter, how it closes and shuts up. We use to say, <hi>We must not praise a fair day till night.</hi> And it was wisely answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:33314:103"/>of him, that was asked his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of two persons, whom he thought the happier, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>that it could not be known which was the happier man till they were dead.</hi> That is well that ends so. Who would not die the death of the righteous, and who would not desire that his latter end might be like his: We see but the <hi>saddest part</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> in this world, the more <hi>lightsom</hi> part remains for us, when we shall be added to the spirits of just men made perfect. Now we have the bitt rest draught, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour keeps the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st wine to the last. The Devil does not do thus. He deals with us as <hi>Jael</hi> did by <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sera,</hi> who gave him fair words, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him with a Mantle, and gives him milk to drink in his thirst: But she conceals the Nail and the Hammer wherewith she opened a way for his soul to flie out.
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:33314:104"/>Thus the Devil does with us, he tells us fair stories of what he will give us, if we will be his servants, but he hides the hook under his bait, he says nothing of the hammer and nail, of the Instruments of death which wait for us.</p>
               <p>Another <hi>Hindrance</hi> is a mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>understanding of the design of Christs Death, and an ill use which we make of it. The most wicked and dissolute will say, he hopes to be saved by the blood of Christ, who died for sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and therefore they think they have no more to do, but strongly to rest themselves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the blood of Jesus, and by that means excuse themselves from an obedience to the Lawes of Christ. But</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:33314:104"/> 1. They make an ill use of the death of Christ and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage themselves in their sinnes, for Christ died not only to deliver us from the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but also from the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> of our sinnes. <hi>He gave himself for us that be might redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie unto himself a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple zealous of good works:</hi> Tit. 2.14. It is true indeed, <hi>There is now no Condemnation to them which are in Christ Jesus.</hi> But who are them? <hi>Who walk not after the Flesh, but after the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is certain, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Christ hath suffered, will do us no good unless we own him to be our Lord and Saviour, unless we repent and believe the Gospel, that is, unless that
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:33314:105"/>we perform the condition of the New Covenant. For though Christ have done his part in order to our recovery, yet he hath let done <hi>ours</hi> also; He hath left us some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do; <hi>viz.</hi> to perform the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ition of the Gospel. We must have a faith and repentance, or else we shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> excluded from the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Gospel. Now we cannot be said to believe in Christ unless we do obey him, unless we receive him as our Lord, otherwise we have but <hi>fansie</hi> for <hi>faith.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>id est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ter homi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> crede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, i. e. side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eo esse, h.e. side-liter Dei mand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere. Salv. de Gub. Dei <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> What says the Scripture in this matter? It tells us, that <hi>Christ being made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> (or being consecrated by his death on the Cross, as the <hi>Jewish</hi> Priests were consecrated by the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Law of <hi>Moses</hi>) <hi>he became the Author of eternal salvation unto all them that obey him,</hi> Heb. 5.9.
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:33314:105"/>Our Saviour tells us plainly, <hi>He that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life; And he that believeth not</hi> (or as it may be very well rendred,) <hi>he that obeyeth not the Son shall not see life;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ssal.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>but the truth of God abideth on him,</hi> John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 36.</p>
               <p>Another great Hindrance is our worldly affairs and business. Our Farms and Yokes of Oxen; the cares of this world, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulness of riches, are the great enemies to Religion and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life. This covetousness made <hi>Judas</hi> betray our Saviour, and the Pharisees <hi>deride</hi> him, and <hi>Dewas forsake</hi> him, and the young man go from him <hi>sorrowful,</hi> the <hi>Gada<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ens weary</hi> of him, and the wicked world <hi>persecute</hi> him in his followers.</p>
               <p>But let such men consider, how sad a bargain it will be to <hi>gain</hi> the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:33314:106"/>
                  <hi>World,</hi> and <hi>lose</hi> their <hi>soul.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can make amends for such a loss: We reade of one <hi>Lysimachus</hi> a King,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarch</hi> de bis qui sero a numin pun.</note> who was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to resign his Kingdom to his enemies for something to allay his heat, and satisfie his thirst, who when he drank, complained of his own calamity, <hi>Who for so short a pleasure should be deprived of so great a Kingdom.</hi> Well may the sinner cry out then, who for a little wealth or honour in this world, hath not only deprived himself of an eternal Kingdom, but lie down also in endless sorrows. How infinitely will this perplex him hereafter, when he shall be in the regions of darkness and of sorrow, to think that he should, in pursuit of the world, lose his soul, and then at once lose his soul and the world too.</p>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:33314:106"/>
               <p> Another <hi>Hindrance</hi> is an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that our sins are greater then can be forgiven: They have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued so long in their great and hainous fins, that they fear they are not now within the reach of mercy. But such a man must know,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That Gods thoughts are not as our thoughts. He tells us, <hi>If the wicked forsake his way, he will have mercy upon him, and he will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly pardon. For,</hi> says he, <hi>my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your ways my ways.</hi> Isa. 55.7, 8. And certainly, there is <hi>not less mercy in the Gospel, then there was under the Law, but more.</hi> Those sins which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law could not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated, will under the Gospel up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our faith and repentance be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given. This is very evident, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us no less in these words,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:33314:107"/>
                     <hi>By him all that believe are justified from all things, from which ye could not be justified by the Law of</hi> Moses, Act. 13.39.</item>
                  <item>2. Christ came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. He came to heal those that were sick. The more sensible we are of our sins and spiritual mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the more need have we of a Saviour, and the greater assurance that he will receive us. <hi>Come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest,</hi> Mat. 11.28. <hi>And him that cometh unto me, I will in no wise cast out,</hi> John 6.37. Thy sins must not discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage thee from coming to Christ, who came into the world for such, and hath received as great sinners as thou art, as you may see 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Such were some of you, but you are washed, &amp;c.</hi> If thy sins be as scarlet, yet if thou art ready to part with them, they shall becom
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:33314:107"/>as white as snow, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18,</item>
               </list>
               <p>The last <hi>Hindrance,</hi> and I fear, the most common is the neglect of the ordinary means of grace, <hi>Faith comes by hearing, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Word of God,</hi> Rom. 10.17. But some are so prophane, and some so proud that they will not hear at all: And for those that do, yet they take no care how they hear: They neither prepare before-hand, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> attend in the service, nor yet consider of it afterwards. The Preacher it looked on as <hi>Lot</hi> was by his sons. <hi>As one that mocks.</hi> And though God have written, and we preach the great things of the Law, they <hi>are counted as a strange thing,</hi> Hos. 8.12. We hear indeed, but we go away and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what manner of persons we were; we go away, nor the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser, nor the better for it; And
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:33314:108"/>that because we came thither with no hearty desires to get more knowledge or more grace: Should God make a search in one of our Assemblies, and proceed from highest to the lowest, he would, I fear, find but few among us that had bin upon our knees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we came together to ask his blessing upon his Word; few that come with any longing desires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the sincere milk of Gods Word, that they might grow thereby. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps some might be found that could not tell for what end they were come together. And so long as we are thus careless and remiss in those things which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for our salvation; 'tis no wonder we proceed to no Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:108"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader, be pleased to take notice that these BOOKS following are sold by <hi>George Calvert</hi> and <hi>Sam. Sprint</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in <hi>Duck-lane.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>GODS TERRIBLE VOICE IN THE CITY;</hi> wherein you have the Sound of the Voice in the History of the two late dreadful Judgments of Plague and of Fire in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> 2. The Interpretation of the Voice in the discovery of the Cause and Design of these Judgments. 14 <hi>Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CHRISTS CERTAIN AND SƲD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEN APPEARANCE TO JƲDG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT.</hi> 4. <hi>Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>FIRE AND BRIMSTONE,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. From Heaven in the barning <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah</hi> freely.</item>
                  <item>2. From Earth, in burning Mount <hi>Aet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a.</hi> lately.</item>
                  <item>3. In Hed, to burn the wicked eternally.</item>
               </list> With the Additions of two Discourses.
<list>
                  <item>1. Concerning the only Delive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er from wrath to come.</item>
                  <item>2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Godliness in Principle and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation. 2. <hi>Edition.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatise concerning the Lords Supper with three Dialogues, for the more full information of the weak, in the nature and use of the Sacrament. By <hi>Thomas Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>little.</hi> 6 <hi>Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:109"/>
            <p> TIME and the End of Time, or two D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mses, the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> about Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tion of time, the second about Considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Latter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd, by <hi>John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> late Minister of the Gospel.</p>
            <p>The <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ints Ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce,</hi> or the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Saving Knowledge. By W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Bare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> late of <hi>Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> in <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Necessi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> disco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ering <hi>Opinion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or a Blou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oi of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om the Hand of Faith. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ot here the Necessity of Faith to be di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed: As also what does not make a Believer, and what does, and the Nerdies<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of all Contentions about Opinion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ted to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>est Capa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty: for the Edification of the Ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and Establishment of the Wave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers. By <hi>Edward W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ill</hi>'s Exposition on the whole Book o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2 Volumes in 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ORY of the Managements of Cardinal <hi>Julio Mazarine,</hi> Chief Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tate of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> written in La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n by Count <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>azza Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldi Prio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and Translated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Original. In which <hi>are</hi> related the principal Successes hapnea from the begining of his Management of Affairs till his Death, <hi>Tom.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Part</hi> I.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33314:109"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>